根據原TLF翻譯的字幕校訂，非RC3字幕
主演：蒂姆·羅賓斯
飾演：Andy Dufresne
主演：摩根·弗堸
飾演：Ellis Boyd 'Red' Redding
片名：《肖申克的救贖》
主演：鮑伯·岡頓
飾演：典獄長 Norton
主演：威廉·桑德勒
飾演：Heywood
主演：克萊希·布朗
飾演：Captain Hadley
主演：吉爾·貝洛
飾演：Tommy
德弗瑞恩先生
Mr. Dufresne, describe...
…描述一下你太太被謀殺當晚，你曾和她談過些什麼？
...the confrontation you had with your wife the night she was murdered.
一些很糟糕的話
It was very bitter.
她說她很高興我已知道，她不想再偷偷摸摸了
She said she was glad I knew, that she hated all the sneaking around.
她說她想離婚
And she said that she wanted a divorce in Reno.
-你當時有什麼反應？ -我對她說我不會在乎的
- What was your response? - I told her I would not grant one.
「在我看見你在雷諾市前，下地獄吧！」
"I'll see you in hell before I see you in Reno."
你的鄰居曾聽你說過這些話吧？
Those were your words, according to your neighbors.
隨他們怎麼說
If they say so.
我當時很不開心，什麼都不記得了
I really don't remember. I was upset.
你和太太爭吵後發生了什麼事？
What happened after you argued with your wife?
她收拾好行李
She packed a bag.
到昆汀先生家堨h了
She packed a bag to go and stay with Mr. Quentin.
格倫·昆汀，職業高爾夫教練
Glenn Quentin, golf pro at the Snowden Hills Country Club...
你知道他是你妻子的情人
... whom you had discovered was your wife's lover.
你跟蹤她了嗎？
Did you follow her?
我先去了幾間酒吧找
I went to a few bars first.
接著，我開車去了昆汀家，但他們不在家
Later, I drove to his house to confront them. They weren't home.
我把車停在街角
I parked in the turnout...
等在那
... and waited.
有何企圖嗎？
With what intention?
我不太確定
I'm not sure.
我非常困惑
I was confused...
還有點醉
... drunk.
我覺得
I think...
我只是想嚇一嚇他們
... mostly I wanted to scare them.
他們到家後，你就進屋殺了他們
When they arrived, you went up to the house and murdered them.
沒有，我控制了自己
I was sobering up.
我開車回家睡覺來忘記一切
I got back in the car and I drove home to sleep it off.
在回家的路上，我把槍扔進了河
Along the way, I threw my gun into the Royal River.
我很肯定這一點
I've been very clear on this point.
但我感到奇怪的是，第二天早上清潔女工發現……
I get hazy where the cleaning woman shows up the following morning...
你太太和她的情人死在床上
...and finds your wife in bed with her lover...
致死的子彈是出自點38口徑的手槍
...riddled with.38-caliber bullets.
德福瑞恩先生，你和我一樣都覺得那是巧合嗎？
Does that strike you as a fantastic coincidence, or is it just me?
確實是巧合
Yes, it does.
你仍堅持說你在兇案發生前
Yet you still maintain you threw your gun into the river...
已經把槍扔進河堣F嗎？
...before the murders took place.
這對你很有利
That's very convenient.
這是事實
It's the truth.
警察在河塈鉹F三天，但他們沒有找到你的槍……
The police dragged that river for three days, and nary a gun was found...
所以無法鑒定
...so no comparison could be made between your gun and the bullets...
死者身上的子彈是否出自你的槍
...taken from the bloodstained corpses of the victims.
這對你來說
And that also...
也非常有利，不是嗎，德福瑞恩先生？
...is very convenient. Isn't it, Mr. Dufresne?
因為我是無辜的……
Since I am innocent of this crime...
所以我發現找不到槍對我非常不利
...I find it decidedly inconvenient that the gun was never found.
各位先生女士，你們聽到了所有的證據
Ladies and gentlemen, you've heard all the evidence.
我們有他犯罪的動機，我們找到他的腳印
We have the accused at the scene of the crime. We have footprints.
留有他的指紋的子彈頭
Bullets on the ground bearing his fingerprints.
打碎的酒瓶上也留有他的指紋
A broken bourbon bottle, likewise with fingerprints.
最重要的是
And most of all...
我們知道他的妻子和她的情人
... we have a beautiful young woman and her lover...
雙雙倒臥在血泊中
... lying dead in each other's arms.
他們是犯了錯
They had sinned.
但他們所犯的錯嚴重到……
But was their crime so great...
……需要用死來贖罪嗎？
... as to merit a death sentence?
當你們考慮時
While you think about that...
請想想這個……
...think about this:
一個彈匣只能裝六顆子彈，而不是八顆
A revolver holds six bullets, not eight.
我肯定這不只是一時衝動而犯下的罪行
I submit that this was not a hot-blooded crime of passion.
那至少是可以理解的，即使不能寬恕
That at least could be understood, if not condoned.
不！
No.
這是復仇
This was revenge...
一個冷血者的復仇，看看這些：
...of a much more brutal, cold-blooded nature. Consider this:
每個死者都身中四槍
Four bullets per victim.
總共是八槍而不是六槍
Not six shots fired, but eight.
那表明子彈打完後
That means that he fired the gun empty...
他還停下來裝子彈
... and then stopped to reload...
以便再次向他們開槍
... so that he could shoot each of them again.
每人多加一槍
An extra bullet per lover...
就在頭部
... right in the head.
德弗瑞恩先生，我覺得你非常冷血
You strike me as a particularly icy and remorseless man, Mr. Dufresne.
看著你都令我毛骨聳然
It chills my blood just to look at you.
我以本州賦予我的權利
By the power vested in me by the state of Maine...
判處你兩項終身監禁
...I hereby order you to serve two life sentences back-to-back...
分別為兩位死者，退庭！
...one for each of your victims. So be it!
坐下來
Sit.
你因被判終身監禁己在此二十年？
We see you've served 20 years of a life sentence?
-是的，先生 -你感到後悔嗎？
- Yes, sir. - You feel you've been rehabilitated?
是的，絕對有，先生
Yes, sir. Absolutely, sir.
我是說，我得到了教訓
I mean, I learned my lesson.
我敢說我已經完全改變了
I can honestly say that I'm a changed man.
我不會再危害社會
I'm no longer a danger to society.
這是神的真理
That's God's honest truth.
「不合格」
嗨，瑞德
Hey, Red.
怎麼樣了？
How'd it go?
不同的日子，同樣的結果
Same old shit, different day.
我知道你的感受的
Yeah, I know how you feel.
我下星期又要被否決了
I'm up for rejection next week.
對，我上星期也被否決了
Yeah, I got rejected last week.
一向如此
It happens.
嗨，瑞德，給我一包煙
Hey, Red, bump me a deck.
滾開！你已欠我五包煙了
Get out of my face, man! You're into me for five packs already.
-是四包！ -五包！
Four!
我想在美國的每個聯邦或州監獄堻ㄕ章釦琱@樣的人物
There must be a con like me in every prison in America.
就是能夠給你搞到東西的傢伙
I'm the guy who can get it for you.
定制的香煙，一包大麻……
Cigarettes, a bag of reefer, if that's your thing...
為慶祝你兒子或女兒高中畢業的一瓶白蘭地， 只要你喜歡
... bottle of brandy to celebrate your kid's high school graduation.
或者幾乎所有東西……
Damn near anything within reason.
是的，先生，我是個冷酷的人
Yes, sir! I'm a regular Sears and Roebuck.
所以1949年當安迪·德福瑞恩來找我
So when Andy Dufresne came to me in 1949...
問能否弄張麗塔·海華絲的圖片進來時 （麗塔·海華絲：Rita，Hayworth）
... and asked me to smuggle Rita Hayworth into the prison for him...
我告訴他沒問題
... I told him, "No problem."
安迪·杜福雷在1947年來到肖申克監獄
Andy came to Shawshank Prison...
罪名是謀殺他的妻子和她的情人
... in early 1947 for murdering his wife and the fella she was banging.
入獄以前，他是波特蘭銀行的副總裁
On the outside, he'd been vice president of a large Portland bank.
對他來說是年青有為
Good work for a man so young.
好啊，瑞德
你會說英語嗎？
You speak English, butt-steak?
跟著這個長官走
You follow this officer.
我一生中從沒見過這麼差勁的人
I never seen such a sorry-Iooking heap of maggot shit in all my life.
過來啊！到這堥
Hey, fish! Come over here!
今天要賭嗎，瑞德？
Taking bets today, Red?
賭煙還是賭錢？
Smokes or coin? Bettor's choice.
香煙，我賭兩根
Smokes. Put me down for two.
好吧，你買哪一個？
All right, who's your horse?
那個又矮又瘦的
That little sack of shit.
-排在第八的，他會是第一個的 -媽的！我也想買他
- Eighth. He'll be first. - Bullshit! I'll take that action.
你輸定了，孩子
You're out some smokes, son.
該你下注了
If you're so smart, you call it.
我買那邊的那個胖子
I'll take that chubby fat-ass there.
排在第五的那個，我賭四根香煙
The fifth one. Put me down for a quarter deck.
今天又有新人
Fresh fish today!
我們又有的玩了
We're reeling them in!
我承認我初次見到安迪的時候，沒什麼特別的感覺
I admit I didn't think much of Andy first time I laid eyes on him.
他看起來似乎風一吹就會倒
Looked like a stiff breeze would blow him over.
這就是我對他的第一印象
That was my first impression of the man.
你買誰？
What do you say?
那個高個子
That tall drink of water with the silver spoon up his ass.
那個人？不可能的
That guy? Never happen.
-我賭十根香煙 -那可是大賭注
- 10 cigarettes. - That's a rich bet.
誰來證明我看錯了？
Who's going to prove me wrong?
海伍德？濟格？
Heywood? Jigger?
史基？
Skeets?
弗洛德？
Floyd!
四個膽小鬼
Four brave souls.
回囚房去，要查房了
Return to your cellblocks for evening count.
所有犯人都回囚房去
All prisoners, return to your cellblocks.
向右轉
Turn to the right!
往前看
Eyes front.
這是哈德利先生，他是這堛漪搹u長
This is Mr. Hadley. He's captain of the guards.
我是諾頓，這堛漕摨貌
I'm Mr. Norton, the warden.
你們都被判有罪了
You are convicted felons.
因此被送到這堥
That's why they've sent you to me.
規則一
Rule number one:
不得褻瀆上帝
No blasphemy.
在我的監獄堣ㄠo有人褻瀆上帝
I'll not have the Lord's name taken in vain in my prison.
其他的條例……
The other rules...
其他的條例，你們慢慢就會知道了，還有問題嗎？
...you'll figure out as you go along. Any questions?
何時吃飯？
When do we eat?
我們叫你吃的時候你就吃
You eat when we say you eat.
叫你去廁所你就去廁所
You shit when we say you shit, and piss when we say you piss.
明白嗎？笨蛋？
You got that, you maggot-dick motherfucker?
站好
On your feet.
我只相信兩樣東西
I believe in two things:
紀律和聖經
Discipline and the Bible.
在這堙A你們兩樣都有
Here, you'll receive both.
把你們的思想交給上帝
Put your trust in the Lord.
你們的身體交給我
Your ass belongs to me.
歡迎來到肖申克監獄
Welcome to Shawshank.
解開他們
Unhook them.
轉過身
Turn around.
夠了
That's enough.
到籠子邊上去
Move to the end of the cage.
轉身，給他消毒
Turn around. Delouse him.
轉身
Turn around.
出來，去領你們的衣服和聖經
Move out of the cage. Pick up your clothes and Bible.
下一個！
Next man up!
往右走
To the right.
右邊，右邊
Right. Right.
左邊
Left.
毫無疑問，第一晚是最難熬的
The first night's the toughest. No doubt about it.
赤裸裸的進囚籠，就像剛出生時那樣
They march you in naked as the day you were born...
消毒藥粉令皮膚像被火燒一樣
... skin burning and half-blind from that delousing shit.
他們把你丟進囚籠
And when they put you in that cell...
關上鐵門
... and those bars slam home...
那時你才感到這是真實的
... that's when you know it's for real.
瞬間過去的一切都離你而去
Old life blown away in the blink of an eye.
剩下的只有對過去的回憶
Nothing left but all the time in the world to think about it.
很多新來的人在第一晚都幾乎發瘋了
Most new fish come close to madness the first night.
有些人甚至還痛哭流涕
Somebody always breaks down crying.
一向都如此的
Happens every time.
唯一的問題是
The only question is...
誰會是第一個呢？
... who's it going to be?
我想那是用來賭博的最佳玩意
It's as good a thing to bet on as any, I guess.
我把賭注押在杜福雷身上
I had my money on Andy Dufresne.
熄燈
Lights out!
我還記得我在這堛熔臚@晚
I remember my first night.
似乎是很久以前的事了
Seems like a long time ago.
嗨，新來的
Hey, fish.
新來的
Fish, fish.
你怕黑嗎？
What are you, scared of the dark?
我打賭，你希望你爸和你媽從沒把你生下來
Bet you wish your daddy never dicked your mama!
蠢豬！
Piggy! Pork! I want me a pork chop.
他們總是喜歡逗新人
The boys always go fishing with first-timers.
不達目的，誓不罷休
And they don't quit till they reel someone in.
嗨，胖子
Hey, Fat Ass.
胖子！
Fat Ass!
聊天吧
Talk to me, boy.
我知道你在那堙A我能聽見你的呼吸聲
I know you're there. I can hear you breathing.
別理別人怎麼說，你聽到嗎？
Don't you listen to these nitwits, you hear me?
這地方沒那麼差勁
This place ain't so bad.
這樣吧
Tell you what...
我介紹你認識他們，就像一家人
...I'll introduce you around, make you feel right at home.
我知道有幾個人
I know a couple of big old bull queers that'd just...
會很樂意認識你的
...Iove to make your acquaintance.
尤其是你那又白又嫩的屁股
Especially that big, white, mushy butt of yours.
天啊！
God!
我不屬於這
I don't belong here!
-嗨，有人贏了 -我要回家
- We have a winner! - I want to go home!
是胖子
And it's Fat Ass by a nose!
新人！
Fresh fish!
我要回家
I want to go home!
我要見我媽媽
I want my mother!
我操過你媽媽！她不怎麼樣
I had your mother! She wasn't that great!
發生了什麼事？
What the Christ is this horseshit?
他講粗話，我要告訴典獄官
He blasphemed. I'll tell the warden.
告訴他我操你屁股吧
You'll tell him with my baton up your ass!
讓我出去
Let me out!
胖子，你想怎麼樣？
What is your malfunction, you fat barrel of monkey spunk?
求求你！我不該在這堛
Please! I ain't supposed to be here.
不該是我
Not me!
我不會警告你的
I won't count to three. Not even to one.
馬上你閉上你的臭嘴，否則有你受的！
You shut up, or I'll sing you a lullaby!
-閉嘴，閉嘴 -求求你……
Shut up, man. Shut up!
你不明白的，我不該在這堛
You don't understand. I'm not supposed to be here.
把囚籠打開
Open that cell.
我也是！這堻Q他們弄得就像監獄
Me neither! They run this place like a fucking prison!
狗娘養的
Son of a bitch!
長官，算了
Captain, take it easy!
如果我今晚聽到有半點聲音
If I hear so much as a mouse fart in here tonight...
我對天發誓，你們會吃不了兜著走
...I swear by God and Jesus, you will all visit the infirmary.
所有的人都不會放過的
Every last motherfucker in here.
把他抬到醫療室去
Call the trustees. Take that tub of shit down to the infirmary.
德福瑞恩第一晚就讓我輸了兩包煙
His first night in the joint, Dufresne cost me two packs of cigarettes.
他整晚一言不發
He never made a sound.
北倉三樓，出來
Tier 3 north, clear count!
北倉二樓，出來
Tier 2 north, clear count.
南倉三樓，出來
Tier 3 south, clear.
準備出來放風
Prepare to roll out.
出去！
Roll out!
你準備吃那個嗎？
Are you going to eat that?
不，我沒這打算
I hadn't planned on it.
你介意嗎？
Do you mind?
你真不錯
That's nice and ripe.
傑克說謝謝你
Jake says thank you.
它從巢堭慾U來了
Fell out of his nest over by the plate shop.
我要照顧它直到它會飛為止
I'm going to look after him until he's big enough to fly.
不！他過來了
Oh, no! Here he comes.
早上好，各位
Morning, fellas.
不錯的早晨，不是嗎？
Fine morning, isn't it?
你們知道我的意思的，對嗎？
You know why it's a fine morning, don't you?
把它們拿出來，把它們排成排……
Send them down. I want them lined up...
非常誘人的一行
...just like a pretty little chorus line.
看看這個
Look at that.
我真受不了了
- I can't stand this guy. - Oh, Lord!
瑞查德、維吉尼亞……
Yes! Richmond, Virginia.
聞我的屁吧
Smell my ass!
再聞聞我的
After he smells mine.
很遺憾，你下注的那個輸了
That's a shame about your horse coming in last and all.
但我很喜歡我下注的那個人
But I sure do love that winning horse of mine, though.
我見到他就要親他一下
I owe that boy a big kiss when I see him.
你為何不把香煙分給他點？
Why don't you give him some of your cigarettes instead? Lucky fuck!
嗨，利奧
Hey, Tyrell.
這周你在醫療室當值是嗎？
You pull infirmary duty this week?
我下注的那個怎麼樣了？
How's my horse doing anyway?
死了
Dead.
哈德利打爆了他的頭
Hadley busted his head up pretty good.
晚上醫生都回家了
Doc had gone home for the night.
可憐的傢伙就在那婼魒鴞迨W
Poor bastard lay there till this morning.
可是那時我們已經無能為力了
By then, there wasn't nothing we could do.
他叫什麼？
What was his name?
你說什麼？
What'd you say?
我只是想問有人知道他的名字嗎？
I was just wondering if anyone knew his name.
關你屁事，新來的？
What the fuck do you care, new fish?
他叫什麼都無所謂了，他已經死了
Doesn't fucking matter what his name was. He's dead.
嗨，有人和你一起嗎？
Anybody come at you yet?
有人喜歡你嗎？
Anybody get to you yet?
嗨，在這塈畯抭˙搨n朋友
Hey, we all need friends in here.
我可以做你的朋友
I could be a friend to you.
難得手
Hard to get.
我喜歡
I like that.
安迪一開始很自閉
Andy kept pretty much to himself at first.
我猜他在想辦法
I guess he had a lot on his mind...
接受牢堛漸肮
... trying to adapt to life on the inside.
一個月以後他才開口
Wasn't until a month went by before he opened his mouth...
和某人談話
... to say more than two words to somebody.
就像你們所看見的
As it turned out...
那個人就是我
... that somebody was me.
我是安迪·德福瑞恩
I'm Andy Dufresne.
殺妻的銀行家
Wife-killing banker.
你為何要殺你的妻子？
Why'd you do it?
我沒有殺她
I didn't, since you ask.
你很適應合這
You're going to fit right in.
這兒每個人都是無辜的，你不知道嗎？
Everybody in here's innocent. Didn't you know that?
-你為進監獄？ -我什麼都沒做，律師害了我
- What you in here for? - Didn't do it. Lawyer fucked me.
聽說你很冷酷
Rumor has it you're a real cold fish.
你以為自己很了不起，對嗎？
You think your shit smells sweeter than most. Is that right?
你怎麼認為呢？
What do you think?
說實話，我還不知道
To tell you the truth, I haven't made up my mind.
我知道你能拿到違禁品
I understand you're a man that knows how to get things.
我能搞到
I'm known to locate certain things from time to time.
你能給我個鶴嘴槌嗎？
I wonder if you might get me a rock hammer.
鶴嘴槌
A rock hammer.
-要幹什麼？ -你關心這個幹嗎？
- What is it and why? - What do you care?
如果是牙刷我就不會問你，我會開個價錢
For a toothbrush, I wouldn't ask. I'd quote a price.
但是牙刷沒有殺傷力，對嗎？
But a toothbrush is a non-lethal object, isn't it?
有道理
Fair enough.
一個鶴嘴槌有六至七英吋長
A rock hammer is about six or seven inches long.
-看起來像個小鋤子 -鋤子？
- Looks like a miniature pickax. - Pickax?
打石用的
For rocks.
-石英 -石英？
Quartz?
還有雲母、頁岩……
And some mica, shale...
石灰岩……
...limestone.
這麼說吧
So?
我收集石頭
So I'm a rock hound.
我想在這堻怳j限度的重操舊業
At least I was in my old life. I'd like to be again.
或許你想用它們攻擊某人
Or maybe you'd like to sink your toy into somebody's skull.
不，我在這堥S有敵人
No, I have no enemies here.
不會？等著瞧吧
No? Wait a while.
話說回來
Word gets around.
那對姐妹花很喜歡你
The Sisters have taken quite a liking to you.
特別是伯格斯
Especially Bogs.
就算跟他們說我不好此道也沒用
Don't suppose it would help if I told them I'm not homosexual.
他們也不是
Neither are they.
是這個地方讓他們這樣
You have to be human first. They don't qualify.
畜牲只知道用暴力，不管他人喜不喜歡
Bull queers take by force. That's all they want or understand.
如果我是你，我會加倍小心
If I were you, I'd grow eyes in the back of my head.
-謝謝你的忠告 -忠告免費
- Thanks for the advice. - Well, that's free.
你知道我擔心什麼
You understand my concern.
就算我有麻煩也不會用鶴嘴槌的
If there's trouble, I won't use the rock hammer.
那我猜你想挖個洞逃出去
Then I'd guess you want to escape. Tunnel under the wall, maybe.
我說漏了什麼？什麼東西這麼好笑
What did I miss? What's so funny?
等你看見鶴嘴槌你就明白了
You'll understand when you see the rock hammer.
買這個東西一般要多少錢？
What's an item like this usually go for?
七美元，五金鋪的零售價
Seven dollars in any rock-and-gem shop.
我一般要加20%
My normal markup's 20 percent.
但這東西很特殊
But this is a specialty item.
風險越大，價錢越高，一口價，10元吧
Risk goes up, price goes up. Let's make it an even 10 bucks.
就10元吧
Ten it is.
你那是浪費錢
Waste of money, if you ask me.
為什麼？
Why's that?
這堛漱H喜歡突擊檢查
Folks around this joint love surprise inspections.
他們找到鶴嘴槌就會被充公
They find it, you're going to lose it.
被他們發現的話，你別把我供出來
If they catch you, you don't know me.
否則的話就別想再和我做生意了，你明白了嗎？
Mention my name, we never do business again.
Not for shoelaces or a stick of gum. Now you got that?
我知道了
I understand.
謝謝你，你叫……
Thank you, Mr...
瑞德
Red.
都叫我瑞德
Name's Red.
這名字怎麼來的？
Why do they call you that?
可能因為我是半個愛爾蘭人吧
Maybe it's because I'm Irish.
我現在明白他們為何看中他了
I could see why some of the boys took him for snobby.
他不太說話
He had a quiet way about him...
一舉一動都不像普通的人
... a walk and a talk that just wasn't normal around here.
他漫步著
He strolled...
就像在公園奡疏B
... like a man in the park without a care or a worry in the world.
像穿了件隱形的外套
Like he had on an invisible coat that would shield him from this place.
可以說
I think it'd be fair to say...
開始我對安迪就有好感
... I liked Andy from the start.
快點！我趕時間的
Let's go! Some of us got a schedule to keep.
快點
Move it! Come on, move it!
你太太對你好嗎？
How you doing? How's the wife treating you?
安迪說得很對
Andy was right.
我最終拿到那玩意
I finally got the joke.
用這東西來挖隧道
It would take a man about 600 years...
起碼要花六百年
... to tunnel under the wall with one of these.
-要書嗎？ -今天不用了
- Book? - Not today.
要書嗎？
Book?
送到德福瑞恩那堨h
Delivery for Dufresne.
德福瑞恩，這是你要的書
Here's your book.
謝謝
Thanks.
漂白粉不夠用了，你再去後面拿點來
We're running low on hexite. Get on back and fetch us up some.
這可以弄瞎你的眼睛
This will blind you.
親愛的
Honey, hush.
你不懂
That's it. You fight!
你越掙扎越過癮
Better that way.
我很想說安迪打贏了
I wish I could tell you Andy fought the good fight...
或者姐妹花放過了他
... and the Sisters let him be.
我希望能這麼說
I wish I could tell you that...
但是監獄不是童話世界
... but prison is no fairy-tale world.
他從沒提起是誰
He never said who did it.
但我們都很清楚
But we all knew.
事情就這樣持續了一段時間
Things went on like that for a while.
監獄堛漸肮○ㄛO常規
Prison life consists of routine...
和更多的常規
... and then more routine.
安迪的臉上經常出現新的傷痕
Every so often, Andy would show up with fresh bruises.
姐妹花不斷地騷擾他
The Sisters kept at him.
有時候他能逃脫
Sometimes he was able to fight them off.
但有時不能
Sometimes not.
對安迪來說
And that's how it went for Andy.
這已經成了他的常規
That was his routine.
我相信最初的兩年是最糟糕的
I do believe those first two years were the worst for him.
我也相信事情再繼續這樣下去
And I also believe that if things had gone on that way...
這個地方會奪去他的精神
... this place would have got the best of him.
但是，在1949年的春天
But then, in the spring of 1949...
上頭決定……
... the powers that be decided:
工廠的屋頂需要重修
The roof of the license-plate factory needs resurfacing.
我需要12名自願者工作一星期
I need a dozen volunteers for a week's work.
你們知道的
As you know...
特殊的工作有特殊的好處
...special detail carries with it special privileges.
這是戶外勞動
It was outdoor detail...
五月是戶外勞動的好時間
... and May is one damned fine month to be working outdoors.
排好隊
Stay in line there.
超過100人報名參加勞動
More than a hundred men volunteered for the job.
威勒斯·E·安戈……
Wallace E. Unger.
艾力斯·瑞丁……
Ellis Redding.
你明白了吧？
Wouldn't you know it?
我和幾個我認識的都被選中了
Me and some fellows I know were among the names called.
安迪·德福瑞恩……
Andrew Dufresne.
這只花了我們每人一包煙的代價
It only cost us a pack of smokes per man.
我當然也像往常一樣賺了20%
I made my usual 20 percent, of course.
德州的律師打長途給我
So this big-shot lawyer calls me long-distance from Texas.
我說，「喂？」
I say, "Yeah?"
他說，「很遺憾，你哥哥死了」
He says, " Sorry to inform you, but your brother just died."
-我很難過 -我並不難過，他是個混蛋
- I'm sorry to hear that. - I'm not. He was an asshole.
離家多年，早就當他死了
Ran off years ago. Figured him for dead.
這個律師對我說
So this lawyer fellow says to me:
「他死的時候很富有」，有價值超過百萬的油井
"He died a rich man." Oil wells and shit. Close to a million bucks.
超過百萬的？
A million bucks?
-有些混蛋的運氣有時候就是好 -有你的份嗎？
- Incredible how lucky some assholes get. - You going to see any of that?
三萬五千塊 那就他留給我的
Thirty-five thousand. That's what he left me.
-美元？ -對
Dollars?
真不錯，就像中了彩
That's great! That's like winning the sweepstakes.
不是嗎？
Isn't it?
笨蛋，你想政府會如何對我？
Dumb shit, what do you think the government will do to me?
他們會拿去一大半
Take a big wet bite out of my ass is what.
可憐的布朗
Poor Byron.
真是走運，嗯？奇恥大辱
Terrible fucking luck, huh? Crying shame.
有些人覺得很糟糕
Some people really got it awful.
安迪，你傻了嗎？
Andy, are you nuts?
看著你的拖把，嘿！
IKeep your eyes on your mop, man!
雖然要交點稅，但你還可以……
You'll pay some tax, but you'll still end up...
也許夠買輛新車，但接著呢？
Yeah, maybe enough to buy a new car, and then what?
你必須為新車上該死的稅，維修和保養
I got to pay tax on the car. Repair...
孩子們會纏著你帶著他們兜風
...maintenance, kids pestering you to take them for a ride all the time.
如果年底算錯了稅金，還要掏自己的腰包
Then if you figure your tax wrong, you pay out of your own pocket.
告訴你！山姆叔叔
I tell you! Uncle Sam!
他只是假仁假義
He puts his hand in your shirt and squeezes your tit till it's purple.
他在找死，繼續幹活吧
- Getting himself killed. - IKeep tarring.
什麼兄弟，呸！
Some brother. Shit!
哈德利先生
Mr. Hadley...
你信任你太太嗎？
...do you trust your wife?
噢，這很有趣
Oh, that's funny.
你給我挨揍的話也許更有趣
You'll look funnier sucking my dick with no teeth.
我是說，你是否會認為她對你不忠？
What I mean is, do you think she'd go behind your back?
讓開點，米特，讓他自己出意外
Step aside, Mert. This fucker's having himself an accident.
他會把他推下去的
He'll push him off!
如果你信任她，你就能……
If you trust her, you can keep...
……拿到三萬五千元
...that 35,000.
-你說什麼？ -三萬五千元
- What did you say? - Thirty-five thousand.
一分不少
All of it.
你最好說明白點，小子，不然你完蛋了
- Every penny. - You better start making sense.
你要拿到這筆錢的話，就把它送給你妻子
If you want to keep it, give it to your wife.
政府允許一次性贈與配偶金額的上限是六萬美元
The IRS allows a one-time-only gift to your spouse for up to $ 60,000.
-胡扯！免稅的嗎？ -免稅的
- Bullshit. Tax-free? - Tax-free.
國稅局一毛錢也拿不走
IRS can't touch one cent.
你是那個謀殺妻子的銀行家嗎？
You're that smart banker that killed his wife.
我為何要相信你？
Why should I believe you? So I can end up in here with you?
這是合法的，你可以去問國稅局，他們會給你同樣的回答
It's legal. Ask the IRS. They'll say the same thing.
我知道即使我不告訴你，你也能查到的
I feel stupid telling you this. I'm sure you would have investigated.
我不需要你來教我怎麼做
I don't need you to tell me where the bear shit in the buckwheat.
當然，但你需要有人幫你逃稅
Of course not. But you do need someone to set it up for you.
你需要請一個律師
That'll cost you. A lawyer.
那些華盛頓的混蛋？
A bunch of ball-washing bastards!
我想我能幫你，那你就能省點錢
I suppose I could set it up for you. That would save you some money.
我幫你填好文件
You get the forms, I'll prepare them...
幾乎是免費的
...nearly free of charge.
我只要求給每個同事三瓶啤酒
I'd only ask three beers apiece for each of my coworkers.
同事？你真的發達了
"Coworkers." That's rich!
一個戶外工作的人能有啤酒喝的話
A man working outdoors feels more like a man...
……會感覺更像一個男人，那是我的意見……
...if he can have a bottle of suds. That's only my opinion...
長官
...sir.
你們在看什麼？
What are you jimmies staring at?
繼續幹活
Let's go! Work!
就這樣
And that's how it came to pass...
在完工前的第二天
... that on the second-to-last day of the job...
在49年的春天堙A一群在工廠上面裝修的罪犯
... the convict crew that tarred the factory roof in the spring of '49...
早上十點坐在屋頂上
... wound up sitting in a row at 10:00 in the morning...
享受著清涼的啤酒和肖申克最嚴密的保護
... drinking icy-cold beer, courtesy of the hardest screw...
這種事在肖申克從沒有發生
... that ever walked a turn at Shawshank State Prison.
趁涼喝，女士們。
Drink up while it's cold, ladies.
他還裝作很大度似的走來走去
The colossal prick even managed to sound magnanimous.
我們坐著喝著啤酒，陽光灑在肩頭，覺得是個自由人
We sat and drank with the sun on our shoulders and felt like free men.
感覺就像在裝修自己家的屋項
We could have been tarring the roof of one of our own houses.
我們就像造物主
We were the lords of all creation.
安迪看起來
As for Andy...
也有點不同了
... he spent that break hunkered in the shade...
他臉上露出奇怪的笑容
... a strange little smile on his face...
望著我們喝他的啤酒
... watching us drink his beer.
要來點嗎？
Want a cold one?
不，謝謝，我戒酒了
No, thanks. I gave up drinking.
如果他不和獄警打交道
You could argue he done it to curry favor with the guards.
或許就不能和我們交上朋友
Or maybe make a few friends among us cons.
我？
Me?
我覺得他這樣做只是為了在此感到自由
I think he did it just to feel normal again...
哪怕只是一小會兒
... if only for a short while.
將軍
IKing me.
象棋，這是一個王者的遊戲，什麼？
- Chess. Now there's a game of kings. - What?
文明，戰略
Civilized. Strategic.
我一點都沒察覺，我討厭這樣
And a total fucking mystery. I hate it.
改天我教教你吧
Let me teach you someday.
好的
Sure.
或許你我可合作
We could get a board together.
你找對人了，我能弄到很多東西
You're talking to the right man. I can get things, right?
我們可以合作做買賣，我來雕刻
We might do business on a board, and I'll carve the pieces myself.
一面是石膏像，另一面是肥皂石，你覺得怎樣？
One side in alabaster, one in soapstone. What do you think?
這需要很多時間
I think it'll take years.
時間不是問題，只是沒有石頭
Years I got. What I don't have are the rocks.
操場堿B到的都是小石頭
Pickings are pretty slim in the yard.
大多是鵝卵石
Pebbles, mostly.
安迪，我們是朋友，對嗎？
We're getting to be kind of friends, aren't we?
我想是的
Yeah, I guess.
我能問你個問題嗎？
Can I ask you something?
你為何要殺你妻子？
Why'd you do it?
我是清白的，瑞德
I'm innocent, Red.
就像這獄中其他人一樣
Just like everybody else here.
你怎會進來的？
What are you in for?
和你一樣，是謀殺
Murder. Same as you.
清白的？
Innocent?
肖申克監獄堸艉@有罪的一個
Only guilty man in Shawshank.
金絲雀在哪堙H
Where's the canary?
你怎麼知道的？
How did you know?
-我怎麼知道？ -原來你不知道
- How did I know what? - So you don't know.
來
Come.
金絲雀就在那
This is where the canary is.
在我家聽到女人唱歌很驚訝是嗎？
Quite a surprise to hear a woman singing in my house, eh?
那確實令我……
That's quite a...
很驚訝
... surprise.
等等
Wait, wait.
她出場了
Here she comes.
我最愛看她擺弄頭髮那場戲
I like this part when she does that shit with her hair.
我知道，這個月已經看了三遍了
I know. I've seen it three times this month.
吉達，你好嗎？
Gilda, are you decent?
我？
Me?
天啊，我喜歡這場戲
God, I love it.
我明白你什麼都弄得到
I understand you're a man that knows how to get things.
是的，要什麼有什麼，你要什麼？
I'm known to locate certain things from time to time. What do you want?
-麗塔·海華絲 -什麼？
- Rita Hayworth. - What?
你能找到她嗎？
Can you get her?
你就是強尼嗎，久聞大名了
So this is Johnny Farrel. I've heard a lot about you.
-要幾個星期的時間 -幾個星期？
- Take a few weeks. - Weeks?
很抱歉，現在她又沒有坐在我的大腿上。
I don't have her stuffed down the front of my pants right now, sorry to say.
但我能找到的
But I'll get her.
放鬆些
Relax.
謝謝
Thanks.
-滾出去！ -我要換帶子了
- Get out! - I got to change reels!
我說了，滾出去
I said fuck off!
你打算大叫嗎？
Ain't you going to scream?
讓我們做個了結吧
Let's get this over with.
他打爆了我的鼻子
He broke my fucking nose!
現在
Now...
我要拉開拉鏈
...I'm going to open my fly...
我給你什麼吃你就吃下什麼
...and you'll swallow what I give you to swallow.
然後再吃羅斯的，你打爆了他的鼻子
Then you'll swallow Rooster's. You broke his nose.
他該得到點補償
He ought to have something to show for it.
我會咬斷任何放進我嘴堛漯F西
You put it in my mouth, you lose it.
不，你還沒明白
No, you don't understand.
你那樣做的話我就把刀插進你的耳朵
Do that and I'll put all eight inches of this in your ear.
好吧，但你得知道突如其來的腦部撞擊
All right, but you should know that sudden, serious brain injury...
會令受害人劇烈反應
...causes the victim to bite down hard.
事實上，我聽說受害者會咬緊牙關
In fact, I hear the bite reflex is so strong...
要用鐵棍
...they have to pry the victim's jaws open...
才能撬開他的嘴巴
...with a crowbar.
你怎麼知道的？
Where do you get this shit?
從書堿搢鴘
I read it.
你不會看書？白癡？
You know how to read, you ignorant fuck?
親愛的
Honey!
你不應該這樣的
You shouldn't!
伯格斯沒有把任何東西放進安迪的嘴
Bogs didn't put anything in Andy's mouth.
他的朋友們也沒有
And neither did his friends.
他們只是把他揍了個半死
What they did do is beat him within an inch of his life.
安迪在療養院媥蒝蓐鬗F一個月
Andy spent a month in the infirmary.
伯格斯則被鎖進黑房關了一周
Bogs spent a week in the hole.
伯格斯，時間到了
Time's up, Bogs.
遵命，頭
It's your world, boss.
回到你的囚倉，等著查房
Return to your cellblocks for evening count.
所有犯人返回囚房
All prisoners report for lock down.
什麼事？
What?
-他要到哪堨h？ -抓住他
- Where's he going? - Grab his ankles.
救命
Help!
之後，有兩件事再也沒發生過了
Two things never happened again after that.
姐妹花再也不敢惹安迪了
The Sisters never laid a finger on Andy again.
而伯格斯再也沒有站起來
And Bogs would never walk again.
他被送到一個特殊醫院去
They transferred him to a minimum-security hospital upstate.
據我所知，他在下半生中……
To my knowledge, he lived out the rest of his days...
都只能靠飲筒來進食
... drinking his food through a straw.
我想給安迪開個歡迎會慶祝他復原
Andy could use a nice welcome back when he gets out of the infirmary.
聽起來很不錯
Sounds good to us.
啤酒的事我們還欠他的情
I figure we owe him that much for the beer.
他喜歡下象棋
The man likes to play chess.
給他找點石頭吧
Let's get him some rocks.
夥計們
Guys!
我找到一塊
I got one.
我找到一塊，看
I got one. Look!
希伍德，那不是皂石，也不是石膏
Heywood, that isn't soapstone! And it ain't alabaster either.
你們他媽的是地質學家嗎？
What are you, a fucking geologist?
他是對的，這不是我們要找的
He's right. It ain't.
-這到底是什麼？ -糞球
- What the hell is it then? - It's a horse apple.
-胡扯！ -不，是馬糞
- Bullshit! - No, horseshit.
曬乾了的
Petrified.
他媽的
Damn!
不久，他們開始認識石頭
Despite a few hitches, the boys came through in fine style.
當安迪在週末回來的時候
And by the weekend he was due back...
我們已經找到足夠多的石頭讓他忙個不停
... we had enough rocks saved up to keep him busy till rapture.
那個星期我也收到很大批貨
Also got a big shipment in that week.
香煙
Cigarettes...
口香糖
... chewing gum...
威土忌
... sipping whisky...
畫著裸女的撲克牌
... playing cards with naked ladies on them. You name it.
當然，最重要的是
And of course, the most important item:
麗塔·海華絲
Rita Hayworth herself.
「歡迎歸來,免費享用」
注意，要查房了
Heads up. They're tossing cells.
Heads up. They're tossing cells!
119房
119.
123房
123.
站起來
On your feet.
面向牆站好
Face the wall.
轉過身面向典獄長
Turn around and face the warden.
很高興看見你在看這本書
Pleased to see you reading this.
特別喜歡哪一章？
Any favorite passages?
看到你，就知道……
"Watch ye, therefore, for ye know not...
你是精神之主
...when the master of the house cometh."
馬可福音第十三章三十五節
Mark 13:35.
我一向都喜歡那一章
I've always liked that one.
但我更喜歡
But I prefer...
我是世界的光
..." I am the light of the world.
跟隨我就不會步入黑暗，而能得到生命的光
Ye that followeth me shall have the light of life."
約瑟福音第八章第十二節
John, chapter 8, verse 12.
我聽說你精通數學
I hear you're good with numbers.
不錯
How nice.
人總得有一技之長
Man should have a skill.
這個你怎麼解釋
Explain this.
這是紗紙，打磨石頭用的
It's called a rock blanket. It's for shaping and polishing rocks.
這是我的小嗜好
A little hobby of mine.
相當乾淨
It's pretty clean.
看來沒什麼古怪的
Some contraband here, but nothing to get in a twist over.
這是未經我批准的
I can't say I approve of this.
但是……
But I suppose...
凡事總有例外
...exceptions can be made.
鎖門！
Lock them up!
差點忘記了
I almost forgot.
我不能取走它的
I'd hate to deprive you of this.
救贖之道就在其中
Salvation lies within.
是的，先生
Yes, sir.
查房其實只是個藉口
Tossing cells was just an excuse.
事實上
Truth is...
諾頓是想考察一下
... Norton wanted to size Andy up.
「主的審判迅速降臨」
我太太在教堂做的
My wife made that in church group.
很不錯，先生
Very nice, sir.
喜歡洗衣房的工作嗎？
You enjoy working the laundry?
不，先生，不是特別喜歡
No, sir. Not especially.
或許我們能做點別的……
Perhaps we can find something more...
利用你的學識
...befitting a man of your education.
傑克，布魯斯呢？
Hey, Jake. Where's Brooks?
安迪，我聽到你來了
I thought I heard you out here.
我來跟你工作
I've been reassigned to you.
我知道，他們跟我說了
I know, they told me.
也是被踢傷的嗎？
Ain't that a kick in the head?
我來帶你看看吧
Well, I'll give you the dime tour.
來吧
Come on.
就在這兒
Well, here she is.
肖申克監獄圖書館
The Shawshank Prison Library.
《國家地理》……
National Geographics...
《讀者文摘》……
...Reader's Digest condensed books...
愛情小說……
...and Louis L'Amour.
雜誌……
Look magazine.
園藝指南
Erle Stanley Gardners.
每晚我推車四處走
Every evening I load up the cart and make my rounds.
名字寫在這板上
I enter the names on this clipboard here.
很容易的工作
Easy, peasy, Japanese-y.
-有問題嗎？ -你當了多久的圖書管理員
- Any questions? - How long have you been librarian?
我1905年入獄，1912年在此工作
I come here in '05, and they made me librarian in 1912.
你一直都有助手嗎？
And have you ever had an assistant?
沒有，工作不是那麼忙
No. Not much to it, really.
那為什麼現在讓我來？
Why me? Why now?
我不知道
I don't know.
但我很高興有個伴
But it'd be nice to have some company down here.
德福瑞恩
就是他
That's him. That's the one.
我叫迪格斯
I'm Dekins.
我想……
I was thinking...
為兒子申請助學金
...about setting up some kind of trust fund for my kids' educations.
我明白了
I see.
坐下來談好嗎？
Why don't we have a seat and talk it over.
布魯斯，你有紙和筆嗎？
Do you have a piece of paper and a pencil?
謝謝
Thanks.
那麼
So...
迪格斯先生
Mister Dekins...
接著安迪問迪格斯
And then Andy says, " Mr. Dekins...
你想讓你的兒子去哈佛還是耶魯？
...do you want your sons to go to Harvard or Yale?"
他沒有這樣說
He didn't say that!
上帝可以作證
As God as my witness!
迪格斯愣了一會兒
Dekins blinked for a second...
傻笑著和安迪握手
...then he laughed and actually shook Andy's hand.
老天！和他握手
- My ass! - Shook his hand.
我告訴你們，我感到……
I tell you, I near soiled myself!
安迪若穿上那套衣服
All he needed was a suit and tie and a jiggly hula gal on his desk...
他就會變成德福瑞恩先生的了
...he'd have been "Mr. Dufresne," if you please.
安迪，又交上新朋友了？
Making a few friends?
我不認為是朋友
I wouldn't say "friends."
我是一個能提供準確財政計劃的謀殺犯
I'm a convicted murderer who provides sound financial planning.
只是某人不錯的僕人
It's a wonderful pet to have.
至少可以令你離開洗衣房
Got you out of the laundry, though.
可能不是那麼簡單的
It might do more than that.
我打算擴大圖書館，找點新書
How about expanding the library. Get some new books.
還是找張檯球桌吧
If you ask for something, ask for a pool table.
你打算怎麼做，我是說
How do you expect to do that? I mean...
怎麼得到新書，向誰請求
...get new books in here, "Mr. Dufresne, if you please."
我會向典獄長要錢
I'll ask the warden for funds.
噢，孩子，孩子，我經歷了六個典獄長，懂得了一條
Six wardens have been through here in my tenure, and I've learned...
一個事實，宇宙真理
...one immutable, universal truth:
那個人還沒有生出來
Not one born whose asshole...
你向他們提出定遭拒絕的
...wouldn't pucker up tighter than a snare drum when you ask for funds.
-預算不夠用 -我知道
- The budget's stretched thin as it is. - I see.
或許我寫信向參議員提出
Maybe I could write the state senate and request funds from them.
只有三種情況能動納稅人的錢
They have only three ways to spend the taxpayers' money for prisons:
多建圍牆、多建牢房和增加監獄
More walls, more bars, more guards.
若你批准，我想嘗試一下，每週一封信
I'd like to try, with permission. A letter a week.
-他們不能永不理會 -當然能夠
- They can't ignore me forever. - Sure can.
如果你寫著高興那就寫吧
But you write your letters if it makes you happy.
我來替你寄出，怎樣？
I'll even mail them for you. How's that?
就這樣，安迪開始每周寫一封信
So Andy started writing a letter a week...
就像他說得那樣
... just like he said.
但如諾頓所說
And like Norton said...
一直都無回覆
... Andy got no answers.
過了四月，安迪已幫半數獄警們報稅
The following April, he did tax returns for half the guards at Shawshank.
後來，全都找他幫忙了
Year after that, he did them all...
連典獄長納稅務都由他處理
... including the warden's.
後來，他們安排
Year after that, they rescheduled the intramural season...
球隊在稅季中比賽
... to coincide with tax season.
所有的球隊都帶著報稅表
The guards on the opposing teams all remembered to bring their W-2s.
所以莫爾斯比監獄……
So Moresby Prison...
配給你一支槍，但要你自己付錢
...issued you a gun, but you paid for it.
對，連手槍皮套也是
Right. The holster too.
那可以減免稅款，你可把它記下來
That's tax-deductible. You can write that off.
是的！安迪就像一個正常的會計師
Yes, sir! Andy was a regular cottage industry.
事實上，在稅季中他如此的忙，允許有一個幫手
In fact, it got so busy at tax time, he was allowed a staff.
瑞德，你可以取1040號表格來嗎？
Could you hand me a stack of 1040s?
每年有一個月離開監獄去木工場做工
Got me out of the wood shop a month out of the year, and that was fine by me.
同時，安迪仍舊不斷的寫信
And still, he kept sending those letters.
安迪、瑞德，布魯斯出事了
It's Brooks.
看著門
Watch the door.
冷靜點，布魯斯
Please, Brooks.
千萬別衝動，放下來！
- Calm the fuck down. - Stay back!
-放下來，該死！ -發生什麼事？
- Stay back, goddamn it! - What's going on?
他突然掏出刀來
One second he's fine, then out come the knives.
有事慢慢商量好嗎？
We can talk about this, right?
沒商量餘地的，我要割斷他的喉嚨
There's nothing to talk about. I'll cut his fucking throat.
他有什麼對不起你？
What's he done to you?
去問獄警吧
It's what they done!
我別無選擇
I got no choice.
我們都知道，你不會傷害海伍德的
You won't hurt Heywood. We all know that.
-對嗎，海伍德？ -是的
- Right, Heywood? - Sure.
他是你的朋友，布魯斯是講道理的
He's a friend of yours, and Brooks is a reasonable man.
對嗎？
Right, guys?
那麼把刀放下，看著我
So put the knife down. Look at me.
把刀放下
Put the knife down.
看看他的脖子
Look at his neck, for God's sake.
看看他的脖子，他在流血
Look at his neck. He's bleeding.
這是唯一
It's the only way...
使我留在這堛瑪鴘k
...they'd let me stay.
你瘋了，你不會這樣做的
This is crazy. You don't want to do this.
放下，放下刀
Put it, put it down.
放鬆
Take it easy.
一切都會好的
You'll be all right.
他？那麼我呢？
Him? What about me?
這個愚蠢的瘋子差點割斷我的喉嚨
Crazy old fool damn near cut my throat!
你就連刮鬍子也比這刮得厲害
You've had worse from shaving.
究竟怎麼會這樣？
What did you do to set him off?
沒什麼，我只是進來和他道別
Nothing. I come in here to say farewell.
難到你沒聽說？他獲得假釋
Ain't you heard? His parole's come through.
我就是不明白，發生什麼了
I just don't understand what happened in there.
老傢伙瘋了
Old man's crazy as a rat in a tin shithouse.
夠了
That's enough out of you.
-我聽說你嚇得尿流 -去你媽的
- Heard he had you shitting your pants. - Fuck you.
不要說了！
IKnock it off.
布魯斯不是瘋了
Brooks ain't no bug.
他只是被體制化了
He's just institutionalized.
體制化？什麼東西？
"Institutionalized," my ass.
他在此已有五十年了，海伍德，五十年！
The man's been in here 50 years, Heywood, 50 years!
這是他唯一認識的地方
This is all he knows.
在這兒，他是個重要的人
In here, he's an important man...
一個有教養的人
...an educated man.
在外面，他什麼都不是
Outside, he's nothing.
只是一個假釋出來的囚犯
Just a used-up con with arthritis in both hands.
申請張借書證都有困難
Probably couldn't get a library card if he tried.
你明白我說的話嗎？
You know what I'm trying to say?
瑞德，我相信你說是屁話
I do believe you're talking out of your ass.
怎麼想隨你吧
You believe whatever you want.
我告訴你，這些圍牆很有趣的
But I tell you these walls are funny.
開始，你恨它們
First you hate them.
接著，你適應了它們
Then you get used to them.
時間久了
Enough time passes...
你開始離不開它們
...you get so you depend on them.
那就是被體制化了
That's "institutionalized."
Shit.
-我永遠不會那樣的 -對嗎？
- I could never get like that. - Oh, yeah?
因為你沒布魯斯那樣長時間在此
Wait till you've been here as long as Brooks.
太對了
Goddamn right.
他們把你送到這堥茈肮
They send you here for life...
這就是他們確實想要做的
...that's exactly what they take.
無論怎樣已經部分達到了
Part that counts, anyway.
我不能再照顧你了，傑克
I can't take care of you no more, Jake.
你走吧
You go on now.
你自由了
You're free.
布魯斯，祝你好運
Good luck, Brooksie.
大家好
Dear fellas:
外面的改變令我難以想像
I can't believe how fast things move on the outside.
老頭，找死啊？
Watch it, old-timer! Want to get killed?
我童年時只見過一次汽車
I saw an automobile once when I was a kid...
但現在到處都是
... but now they're everywhere.
世界在一片巨大的忙碌之中
The world went and got itself in a big damn hurry.
假釋委員會給我安排了中途宿舍
The parole board got me into this halfway house...
叫做「釀酒人」
... called "The Brewer"...
和一份工作
... and a job...
在一家雜貨店堨]裝食物
... bagging groceries at the Food-Way.
雖然很辛苦，但我很努力工作
It's hard work and I try to keep up...
我的手經常感到酸痛
... but my hands hurt most of the time.
記得用兩層袋
Make sure your man double-bags.
上次幾乎穿底了
Last time, the bottom near came out.
聽到那女士說的嗎？
Make sure you double-bag like the lady says. Understand?
是的，先生
Yes, sir. Surely will.
我想那店主不太喜歡我
I don't think the store manager likes me very much.
有時工作完後，我到公園堨h餵那些鴿子
Sometimes after work, I go to the park and feed the birds.
我一直希望
I keep thinking...
傑克會飛來和我打招呼
... Jake might just show up and say hello.
但它從未來過
But he never does.
我希望，不管在哪，它都過的很好，又交到新朋友
I hope, wherever he is, he's doing okay and making new friends.
晚上我不能入睡
I have trouble sleeping at night.
經常作惡夢，身體像一直往下掉
I have bad dreams like I'm falling.
醒來時感到恐懼
I wake up scared.
要想一會兒才知道自己在哪兒
Sometimes it takes me a while to remember where I am.
也許我該用槍打劫，讓他們好送我回家
Maybe I should get a gun and rob the Food-Way so they'd send me home.
我可以打死那個店主，當作額外補助
I could shoot the manager while I was at it. Sort of like a bonus.
但我已經太老了，再也幹不了這種蠢事
I guess I'm too old for that sort of nonsense anymore.
我不喜歡這地方
I don't like it here.
它令我感到害怕，我決定……
I'm tired of being afraid all the time. I've decided...
離開
... not to stay.
我懷疑他們會爭論
I doubt they'll kick up any fuss...
但不是為我這個老壞蛋
... not for an old crook like me.
「老布來此一遊」
我懷疑他們會爭論，但不是為我這種老壞蛋
"I doubt they'll kick up any fuss, not for an old crook like me.
另外，跟海伍德說，上次的事很對不起，別放在心上
P.S. Tell Heywood I'm sorry I put a knife to his throat.
不再有痛苦的感覺了，布魯斯
No hard feelings. Brooks."
他應該死在這兒
He should have died in here.
你該死的做了什麼？
What the fuck have you done?
一團糟，我來告訴你
It's a goddamn mess, I'll tell you that.
-這些都是什麼？ -你告訴我，全都寄給你的
- What's all this? - You tell me. They're addressed to you.
拿著
Take it.
親愛的德弗瑞恩先生
"Dear Mr. Dufresne:
應你的來信請求，州政府撥給……
In response to your inquiries...
你的圖書館計劃經費
...the state has allocated the enclosed funds for your library project."
這是200元
This is $ 200.
而州立圖書館
"In addition, the library district has generously responded...
捐出舊書和日常用品
...with a donation of used books and sundries.
這些應是你所需要的，而此事亦告一段落
We trust this will fill your needs. We now consider the matter closed.
懇請閣下勿再來信
Please stop sending us letters."
典獄長回來前要清理好
Clear all this out before the warden gets back.
知道
Yes, sir.
安迪，真不錯
Good for you, Andy.
哦！
Wow!
只用了六年時間
It only took six years.
由現在起，我每星期寫兩封信
From now on, I'll write two letters a week instead of one.
你真的很瘋狂，把這兒清理乾淨
I believe you're crazy enough. Get this stuff out...
照他說的辦
...like he said.
我去廁所
I've got to pinch a loaf.
回來時
When I come back...
不想見到這些書
...this is all gone, all right?
安迪，聽到了嗎？
Do you hear that?
德弗瑞恩！
Dufresne!
安迪，讓我出去
Andy, let me out!
安迪
我到今天也沒不明白，這兩個意大利女人在唱著什麼
I have no idea to this day what those two Italian ladies were singing about.
事實上，我也不想去明白
Truth is, I don't want to know.
有些東西不說更好
Some things are best left unsaid.
我想那是，如此的美
I like to think it was something so beautiful...
無法用語言來形容
... it can't be expressed in words...
美得讓你心痛
... and makes your heart ache because of it.
我告訴你，那聲音飛翔
I tell you, those voices soared...
比在這個灰暗地方的任何一個人夢想的都要高遠
... higher and farther than anybody in a gray place dares to dream.
像一隻美麗的小鳥，飛進了我們這灰色的鳥籠
It was like a beautiful bird flapped into our drab cage...
讓這些圍牆消失了
... and made those walls dissolve away.
在那一刻
And for the briefest of moments...
每個在肖申克的落伍者，感到了的自由
... every last man at Shawshank felt free.
但那令典獄長極度憤怒
It pissed the warden off something awful.
開門
Open the door.
開門！
Open it up!
德弗瑞恩，開門
Dufresne, open this door!
把它關掉！
Turn that off!
我警告你，德弗瑞恩！把它關掉
I am warning you. Turn that off!
德弗瑞恩
你落到我手堣F
You're mine now.
安迪被關禁閉兩周
Andy got two weeks in the hole for that little stunt.
站起來
On your feet.
-看看誰回來了 -大藝術家！
- Hey, look who's here. - Maestro!
你就不能放些好聽的嗎，嗯？比如漢克.威廉姆斯！
You couldn't play something good, huh? Like Hank Williams?
還沒來得及接受點播，他們就破門進來了
They broke the door down before I could take requests.
-被關了兩周，值得嗎？ -那是我最好的時光
- Was it worth two weeks? - Easiest time I ever did.
沒有被關小號容易過的事，那個地方一個星期就像一年
- No such thing as easy time in the hole. - A week in the hole is like a year.
對，我有莫扎特先生陪我
- Damn straight. - I had Mr. Mozart to keep me company.
他們讓你帶留聲機到那兒？
So they let you tote that record player down there, huh?
它就在這兒
It was in here.
在這兒
In here.
這就是音樂的魅力，他們……
That's the beauty of music. They...
不能把它從你這兒奪走
...can't get that from you.
你們從沒此感覺嗎？
Haven't you ever felt that way about music?
我年輕時曾學過吹口琴
Well, I played a mean harmonica as a younger man.
可是，現在已經失去興趣了
Lost interest in it, though.
因為在這堥S有任何意義
Didn't make much sense in here.
這堣~是它最有意義的地方
Here's where it makes the most sense.
你需要它就不會忘記它
You need it so you don't forget.
忘記？
Forget?
忘記有一些
Forget that there are...
地方
...places...
在這個世界上，不是用石頭圍成
...in the world that aren't made out of stone.
有些東西……
There's something...
在內心……
...inside...
不能到達……
...that they can't get to...
……不能觸摸
...that they can't touch.
屬於你
That's yours.
你在說什麼？
What are you talking about?
希望
Hope.
我告訴你，我的朋友
Let me tell you something, my friend.
希望是很危險的東西
Hope is a dangerous thing.
希望會讓人瘋狂
Hope can drive a man insane.
它在這兒沒用
It's got no use on the inside.
你最好習慣這想法
You'd better get used to that idea.
就像布魯斯？
Like Brooks did?
坐下
Sit down.
你因終身監禁在此三十年
Says here that you've served 30 years of a life sentence.
覺得自己被改造了嗎？
You feel you've been rehabilitated?
是的，先生
Oh, yes, sir.
毫無疑問
Without a doubt.
老實說我己改過
I can honestly say I'm a changed man.
我已不會危害社會
No danger to society here.
上帝可以作證
God's honest truth.
真的改變了
Absolutely rehabilitated.
「不合格」
三十年
Thirty years.
當你這樣說時
Jesus, when you say it like that...
想過是怎樣過的嗎？
You wonder where it went.
我在想十年是怎樣過去的
I wonder where 10 years went.
這兒
Here.
這是慶祝你假釋被拒絕的禮物
A little parole rejection present.
打來看看吧
Go ahead and open it.
跟你的競爭對手買的
Went through one of your competitors.
別介意，我想讓它給你一個驚喜
I hope you don't mind. I wanted it to be a surprise.
它真漂亮
It's very pretty.
謝謝你
Thank you.
你會用它來吹奏嗎？
You going to play it?
不
No.
不會是現在
Not right now.
關上！
Roll in!
「這個新女孩給你紀念十週年，安迪」
熄燈
Lights out!
安迪說到做到……
Andy was as good as his word.
他每周寫兩封信
He wrote two letters a week instead of one.
1959年，州議員最後終於面對現實
In 1959, the state senate finally clued in to the fact...
那200元的支票起不了作用
... they couldn't buy him off with just a $ 200 check.
最後通過每年撥款500元
Appropriations Committee voted an annual payment of $500...
來讓他閉嘴
... just to shut him up.
隨後安迪所說的令你感到更意外
And you'd be amazed how far Andy could stretch it.
他跟讀書會和慈善機構談至
He made deals with book clubs, charity groups.
他用剩下來的錢來買書
He bought remaindered books by the pound...
《金銀島》
Treasure Island.
羅伯特·路易斯……
Robert Louis...
斯蒂文森
Stevenson.
科幻類，冒險類
Fiction, adventure.
下一本是什麼？
What's next?
是汽車修理
I got here Auto Repair...
和肥皂雕刻技術
...and Soap Carving.
技術與愛好，教育性那一欄
Trade skills and hobbies. Under "Educational," behind you.
《基督山伯爵》
Count of Monte Crisco.
那書不值一看
That's "Cristo," you dumb shit.
作者是亞歷山大……
By Alexandree...
……什麼……馬
...Dum-ass.
「草泥馬」
Dumb ass.
「草泥馬」？
Dumb ass?
是大仲馬。德弗瑞恩，知道那是什麼故事嗎？
Dumas. IKnow what that's about?
講越獄的，你喜歡看的
You'd like it. It's about a prison break.
那我覺得應該發到「教育類」，對吧？
We ought to file that under "Educational" too, oughtn't we?
我們其餘的隨時盡可能幫忙
The rest of us did our best to pitch in when and where we could.
到了肯尼迪遇刺那一年
By the year Kennedy was shot...
安迪把一個充滿松脂味的儲藏間
... Andy had transformed a storage room smelling of turpentine...
變成了新英格蘭州最好的的監獄圖書館
... into the best prison library in New England...
那埵陶怞n的漢克威廉姆斯唱片集
... complete with a fine selection of Hank Williams.
那也是諾頓典獄長髮展大計的一年
That was also when Warden Norton...
推廣他著名的「內在改造」計劃
... instituted his famous "Inside Out" program.
你可能從報紙上讀到過
You may remember reading about it.
所有的媒體都刊出他的照片
It made the papers and got his picture in Look magazine.
這不是放任的方式
It's no free ride...
……而是一種真正的進步
...but rather a genuine progressive advance...
……讓犯人恢復道德
...in corrections and rehabilitation.
收容人被適當的監督
Our inmates, properly supervised...
使他們能在外面工作
...will be put to work outside these walls...
為大眾服務
...performing all manner of public service.
他們會懂得勞動的價值
These men can learn the value...
為社會服務的誠實勞動
...of an honest day's labor and provide a service to the community...
在最低耗支情況下，來利用納稅人的金錢
...at a bare minimum of expense to Mr. And Mrs. John Q. Taxpayer.
當然，諾頓沒有跟報界說
Of course he didn't tell the press...
「最低耗支」其實是相當不確切的說法
... that "bare minimum of expense" is a fairly loose term.
有很多辦法能瞞天過海的
There are 100 different ways to skim off the top.
人力，物力，你說多少就多少
Men, materials, you name it.
上帝，錢是這樣滾入！
And oh, my Lord, how the money rolled in!
繼續這樣，我不用幹了
At this rate, you'll put me out of business.
有這些勞工，你可比這鎮上的承包商出更低價
With this pool of slave labor, you can underbid any contractor in town.
我們提供有用的社區勞務
We're providing a valuable community service.
對報界來說很動聽，但我要養家活口的
That's fine for the papers, but I've got a family to feed.
我們走得太遠
We go back a long way.
我需要這份公路的合同，如果拿不到我就完了
I need this highway contract. I don't get it and I go under. That's a fact.
嘗嘗我的妻子給你特製的陷餅吧
You have some of this fine pie...
好好考慮一下
...my missus made for you. You think about that.
如果我是你對此合同並不擔心
I wouldn't worry too much about this contract.
我已把人手派至別處
I already got my boys committed elsewhere.
謝謝你太太的糕餅
You be sure and thank Maisie for this fine pie.
每筆暗盤交易下
And behind every shady deal...
賺來的每一分錢
... behind every dollar earned...
都是由安迪來作記錄的
... there was Andy, keeping the books.
兩筆存款
Two deposits.
文尼國際和新格蘭，一天又過去了
Maine National and New England First. Night drops as always, sir.
-把我的東西拿到洗衣房 -兩套衣服要乾洗的，還有架上的袋子
Get my stuff to the laundry. Two suits for dry-clean and a bag of whatnot.
如果他們再把我的襯衫漿過了頭，有他們好受的
If they over-starch my shirts again, they'll hear from me.
我看上去怎麼樣？
How do I look?
-很不錯 -這是盛大的慈善晚會
- Very nice. - Big charity to-do up Portland way.
州長也會出席
Governor will be there.
你要剩下的這些嗎？
You want the rest of this?
烤的太難吃
Woman can't bake worth shit.
謝謝，長官
Thank you, sir.
我聽說這樣的派，他收了不少
He's got his fingers in a lot of pies, from what I hear.
他有你想像不到的手段，回扣、酬金..
He's got scams you haven't even dreamed of. IKickbacks on his kickbacks.
黑錢像河一樣流過這
A river of dirty money running through here.
但他遲早得解釋錢是從何而來的
Sooner or later, he'll have to explain where it came from.
這就是我牽涉其中的原因
That's where I come in.
我安排了一切來過濾
I channel it. Filter it. Funnel it.
股票、債券、市政免稅……
Stocks, securities, tax-free municipals.
我把錢送到外面，等它們回來的時候……
I send it out into the real world, and when it comes back...
-純潔得就像個處女 -像洗衣機
- Clean as a virgin's honeypot, huh? - Cleaner.
到諾頓退休的時候，我已讓他成為百萬富翁了
By the time Norton retires, I'll have made him a millionaire.
如果被他們抓住的話，他將在自己的監獄穿上這樣的號碼服
If they ever catch on, he'll wind up in here wearing a number himself.
看來你對我沒有信心
I thought you had more faith in me than that.
我知道你很能幹，但是總會蛛絲馬跡留下
I know you're good, but all that paper leaves a trail.
只要有人想細查，FBI，國稅局
Now anybody gets curious, FBI, IRS...
不管怎樣
...whatever.
總會有人被牽扯
It'll lead to somebody.
是的，但不會是我，也不會是典獄長
Sure it is, but not to me, and certainly not to the warden.
那會是誰？
All right, who?
蘭度·史蒂文
Randall Stevens.
誰？
Who?
從不出聲的拍檔
The "silent" silent partner.
他是帳戶的持有者，他才有罪
He's the guilty one, the man with the bank accounts.
他那堿O過濾黑錢過程的起點
It's where the filtering process starts.
不管他們如何調查，都只會查到他
They trace anything, it'll just lead to him.
他是什麼人？
But who is he?
他是一個幻影，幽靈，是兔子哈維的第二個表弟
He's a phantom, an apparition. Second cousin to Harvey the Rabbit.
我憑空……
I conjured him...
造出他來
...out of thin air.
他只存在於文件中罷了
He doesn't exist, except on paper.
你不能只這麼捏造一個人
You can't just make a person up.
當然可以，如果你知道我們社會系統的漏洞
Sure you can, if you know how the system works.
吃驚的是郵政就能幫你做到
It's amazing what you can accomplish by mail.
史蒂文先生有出生證明書
Mr. Stevens has a birth certificate...
駕駛執照和社會編號
...driver's license, Social Security.
你在說笑
You're shitting me.
他們追查帳戶的話，只是在追查
If they trace any accounts, they'll wind up chasing...
我幻想出來的人
...a figment of my imagination.
喔，該死
Well, I'll be damned!
我沒說過你很能幹嗎？
Did I say you were good?
該死，你簡直是倫勃朗
Shit, you are Rembrandt.
有趣的是
The funny thing is...
……在外面，我是個誠實的人，正直得像桿直箭
...on the outside, I was an honest man, straight as an arrow.
變成騙子就不得不到監獄堥
I had to come to prison to be a crook.
你擔心過嗎？
Ever bother you?
我沒參與，我只是處理收益
I don't run the scams. I just process the profits.
一條好的分界線，也許吧
A fine line, maybe...
不過我也建起了圖書館
...but I also built that library...
來幫助囚犯取得高中文憑
...and used it to help guys get their high school diploma.
你可知他會何會讓我做所有這些？
Why do you think he lets me do all that?
讓你開心，好幫他「清洗」……
IKeep you happy and doing the laundry.
洗的是錢而非床單
Money instead of sheets.
讓我工作輕鬆，那是交易
Well, I work cheap. That's the tradeoff.
湯姆·威廉姆斯1965年到肖申克監獄服刑
Tommy Williams came to Shawshank in 1965...
因非法入室行竊，被判兩年監禁
... on a two-year stretch for B and E.
那是對私人的非法入侵
That's breaking and entering to you.
警察在佩妮家後門抓到，他在電視旁鬼鬼祟祟的
Cops caught him sneaking TV sets out the back door of a JC Penney.
年輕的朋克
Young punk.
「搖滾」先生
Mr. Rock 'n' Roll...
過於自大
... cocky as hell.
快點，老傢伙們，慢得跟糖漿一樣
Come on, old boys. Moving like molasses!
我乾著急
Making me look bad.
我們馬上就喜歡上他了
We liked him immediately.
我從後門出來，像這樣捧著電視機
I'm backing out the door and I got the TV like this.
一件大的老傢伙，我都看不到了，然後我聽到這個聲音
A big old thing. I couldn't see shit. Then I hear this voice.
別動，舉起手來！
"Freeze, kid, hands in the air."
我站在那堙A捧著電視機，他又說：
I was standing there, holding onto that TV. Finally the voice says:
「你聽到我說的嗎？」，我說，「是的，先生」
"You hear what I said, boy?" I say, " Yes, sir. I did.
但我掉落東西，你會告我毀壞他人財物
But if I drop this, you get me on destruction of property too."
你曾在卡士文服刑，是嗎？
You done some stretch in Cashman, right?
是的，那兒要好過得多
Yeah, that was an easy piece of time, let me tell you.
週末有休假，工作也很有計劃
Weekend furloughs. Work programs.
不像這
Not like here.
看來你在新英格蘭都呆在車
Sounds like you done time all over.
我十三歲出道，哪堻ㄔh過
I've been in and out since I was 13.
說說看，也許我也去過那
Name it, chances are I've been there.
也許你應轉行了
Perhaps you should try a new profession.
我是說
What I mean is...
……你不是個一流的小偷，你該試試別的
...you're not a very good thief. You should try something else.
是嗎？你以為你懂這個？
Yeah, what the hell you know about it, Capone?
你怎會進來的？
What are you in for?
我嗎？
Me?
律師坑了我
A lawyer fucked me.
這兒所有人都是無辜的，你不知道嗎？
Everybody's innocent in here. Don't you know that?
後來知道，湯姆竟然有妻子和剛出生的女兒
As it turned out, Tommy had himself a young wife and a new baby girl.
也許他想到她們在街上流蕩
Maybe he thought of them on the streets...
孩子長大卻不知道父親是誰
... or his child growing up not knowing her daddy.
不管為什麼，總之
Whatever it was...
他竟努力起來了
... something lit a fire under that boy's ass.
我想考取高校文憑
Thought I might try for my high school equivalency.
聽說你已經幫了很多人了
Hear you helped a couple of fellas with that.
我不會在失敗者身上浪費時間的
I don't waste time with losers, Tommy.
我再也不是失敗者了
I ain't no goddamn loser.
-你當真？ -是
- You mean that? - Yeah.
你真的是認真的？
You really mean that?
是的，先生，絕對是真的
Yes, sir, I do.
好，因為我們要做就要……
Good. Because if we do this...
……有始有終，絕對不能半途而廢
...we do it all the way, a hundred percent, nothing half-assed.
問題是……
Thing is, see...
我識字不多
...I don't read so good.
好吧
"Well."
你不識字
You don't read...
就這樣
...so well.
我們就由它開始
We'll get to that.
就這樣，安迪開始給湯姆上課
So Andy took Tommy under his wing.
從最基礎的字母開始教
Started walking him through his ABC's.
湯姆學得很快
Tommy took to it pretty well too.
從不知道自己的聰明
Boy found brains he never knew he had.
沒過多久，安迪開始教他課程內容
Before long, Andy started him on his course requirements.
他很喜歡這個孩子
He really liked the kid.
幫一個孩子上進讓他很快樂
Gave him a thrill to help a youngster crawl off the shit heap.
但那不是唯一的原因
But that wasn't the only reason.
監獄堛漱擗l很緩慢
Prison time is slow time.
要用某些事情來消磨時間
So you do what you can to keep going.
有人收集郵票
Some fellas collect stamps.
有人收集火柴盒
Others build matchstick houses.
安迪建起了圖書館
Andy built a library.
現在他需要新的計劃
Now he needed a new project.
那就是湯姆
Tommy was it.
那和他多年來雕磨石頭的原因一樣
It was the same reason he spent years shaping and polishing those rocks.
也如同他把美女的畫像掛在牆上的原因
The same reason he hung his fantasy girlies on the wall.
在監獄
In prison...
一個人不能讓心堛霾
... a man will do most anything to keep his mind occupied.
在1966年，湯姆剛要參加考試的時候
By 1966, right about the time Tommy was getting ready to take his exams...
可愛的瑞奎爾（Raquel）出現了
... it was lovely Raquel.
時間到
Time.
好了嗎？
Well?
真的是一團糟
Well, it's for shit.
我白花了一年時間在這狗屎上面
I wasted a whole year of my time with this bullshit.
也許沒有你想的那麼糟
It's probably not that bad.
比我想像中的還要糟，就像在考中文
I didn't get a thing right. It might as well have been in Chinese.
看看你得了多少分？
Let's see how the score comes out.
我來告訴你吧
I'll tell you how the goddamn score comes out.
兩分
Two points, right there!
那就是你該死的考試
There's your goddamn score!
什麼貓爬上樹，5乘以5是25
Goddamn cats crawling up trees, 5 times 5 is 25...
去死吧
Fuck this place!
他媽的
Fuck it!
我感覺很差
I feel bad.
我令他失望了
I let him down.
不是這樣，孩子
That's crap, kid.
他以你為榮
He's proud of you.
我跟他是老朋友，我很清楚他的性格
We're old friends, I know him as good as anybody.
聰明的夥伴，不是嗎？
Smart fellow, ain't he?
就像剛進來時一樣聰明，他以前是個銀行家
Smart as they come. He was a banker on the outside.
他為什麼被抓進來？
What's he in here for anyway?
謀殺
Murder.
你說什麼？
The hell, you say.
人不可以貌相
You wouldn't think it to look at the guy.
在床上捉到妻子和一個高爾夫選手，把他們兩個一起解決了
Caught his wife in bed with some golf pro. Greased them both.
怎麼了?
What?
大約四年前
About four years ago...
我在湯瑪斯獄服刑
...I was in Thomaston on a two-to-three stretch.
我偷了一輛車
I stole a car.
這是很不應該的事
It was a dumb-fuck thing to do.
在出獄前六個月
About six months left to go...
我有了個新同房
...I get a new cellmate in.
艾馬·布萊奇
Elmo Blatch.
一個強壯、暴躁的混蛋
Big, twitchy fucker.
人見人憎的那種，明白我的意思嗎？
IKind of roomie you pray you don't get. You know what I'm saying?
刑期是六到十二年，持械搶劫
Six-to-twelve, armed burglary.
他說自己犯了不少案子
Said he pulled hundreds of jobs.
難以相信，他很容易激動，你放個屁，他就暴跳如雷
Hard to believe, high-strung as he was. You cut a loud fart, he jumped three feet.
整天說個不停，從不閉嘴
Talked all the time too. That's the other thing. He never shut up.
他談他去過的地方
Places he'd been in...
他幹過的案子，上過的女人
...jobs he'd pulled, women he fucked.
和他殺的人
Even people he killed.
那些讓他不爽的人
People who "gave him shit."
他是這麼說的
That's how he put it.
有天晚上，我開玩笑的說
So one night, like a joke...
我問他，艾馬，你殺了誰？
...I say to him, "Elmo, who did you kill?"
他說……
So he says:
有次我在鄉村俱樂部打工
I got me this job one time, busing tables at a country club...
看到來的人都非富則貴
...so I could case all these big rich pricks that come in.
所以我選了一個傢伙
So I pick out this guy...
有天晚上到他家堨h
...go in one night...
搶劫東西
...and do his place.
他醒過來
He wakes up...
令我很不爽
...and gives me shit.
所以我殺了他
So I killed him.
他和他的情婦
Him and this tasty bitch he was with.
那是最精彩的部分
And that's the best part.
她在和這個職業高爾夫球手做愛
She's fucking this prick, see...
但她是個有夫之婦
...this golf pro, but she's married to some other guy.
她丈夫是個銀行家
Some hotshot banker.
而他竟成了替罪羊
And he's the one they pinned it on.
這是我聽過的最震驚的故事
I have to say that's the most amazing story I ever heard.
更讓我吃驚的是，你竟然相信了它
What amazes me most is you'd be taken in by it.
先生？
Sir?
很明顯威廉姆斯很喜歡你
It's obvious this fellow Williams is impressed with you.
他知道你的事後想讓你振作起來
He hears your tale of woe and naturally wants to cheer you up.
他還年輕，不怎麼明事理
He's young, not terribly bright.
他根本不明白這對你意味著什麼，這並不奇怪
It's not surprising he wouldn't know what a state he put you in.
獄長，他講的是事實
Sir, he's telling the truth.
就說這個，如果有布萊奇這個人的話
Let's say for the moment this Blatch does exist.
你認為他會跪下來，哭著說「是我做的，我坦白」
You think he'd just fall to his knees and cry, " Yes, I did it. I confess.
方便的話，給我加個終身監禁吧
By the way, add a life term to my sentence."
但是湯姆的證供能讓我的案子重審
With Tommy's testimony, I can get a new trial.
前提是布萊奇在那獄中
That's assuming Blatch is still there.
也許他現在已經獲釋了
Chances are, he'd be released by now.
他們應該有他的住址的
They'd have his last known address.
這是個機會，對嗎？
It's a chance, isn't it?
你怎會這麼愚蠢？
How can you be so obtuse?
什麼？
What?
你說什麼？
What did you call me?
愚蠢，這是故意說的？
Obtuse. Is it deliberate?
你忘記你自己的身份了
You're forgetting yourself.
俱樂部會有他的工作記錄卡的記錄……
The country club will have his old timecards.
和有他名字的報稅表
Records, W-2s with his name on them.
你要繼續幻想的話，那是你的事
If you want to indulge this fantasy, it's your business.
不要影響我，談話結束
Don't make it mine. This meeting is over.
如果我能出去的話，我不會提起這媯o生的一切
If I got out, I'd never mention what happens here.
我可以繼續為你洗黑錢
I'd be as indictable as you for laundering that money.
永遠不許和我提錢的事，你這個婊子養的
Don't ever mention money to me, you son of a bitch!
不許在這間辦公室
Not in this office...
不許在任何地方
...not anywhere. Get in here, now!
進來
I just wanted to put you at ease, that's all.
我只是想讓你放心，沒別的意恩
-禁閉室，一個月 -是，長官
Solitary. A month.
你怎麼了？
What's wrong with you?
把他帶出去
Get him out of here.
這是我出去的唯一的機會
This is my chance to get out!
這是我的人生！你明白嗎？
It's my life! Understand?!
帶他出去！帶他出去！
Get him out!
關禁閉一個月
A month in the hole.
這是我聽到過的最嚴厲的懲罰
That's the longest stretch I ever heard of.
這都是我的錯
It's all my fault.
廢話
Bullshit.
事情不是由你而起的，或讓他入罪
You didn't pull the trigger or convict him.
你是說安迪是清白的？
Are you saying Andy is innocent?
我是說，真真正正的無辜的？
I mean, for real innocent?
看起來是
It looks that way.
天啊
Sweet Jesus.
他到這埵釵h久了？
How long has he been here now?
1947，那是多少，19年
1947. What is that? Nineteen years.
-湯姆·威廉姆斯 -是，在這
- Williams, Thomas. - Yeah, over here.
這是什麼？
What you got?
校董會來的信
Board of Education.
他竟把它寄出去了
That son of a bitch mailed it.
你會打開它嗎？還是打自己的屁股？
You going to open it or stand there with your thumb up your butt?
打自己的屁股聽起來好一點
Thumb up my butt sounds better.
把它還給我，你他媽的
Skeets, come on. Give me that, you shithead.
別這樣
Floyd, come on.
請你扔掉它，好嗎？
Will you throw that away, please?
他媽的
Well, shit.
那孩子通過了，平均C+
The kid passed. C + average.
我想你會喜歡的
Thought you'd like to know.
典獄長要見你
Warden wants to talk.
就在這堙H
Out here?
他是這麼說的
That's what the man said.
典獄長？
Warden?
湯米
湯姆，我要你保證這次談話只有我們兩個知道
I'm asking you to keep this conversation just between us.
我感到很艱難
I feel awkward enough as it is.
這事的情形很特別
We got a situation here.
我想你可以體會到
I think you can appreciate that.
是的
Yes, sir.
我肯定
I sure can.
告訴你，孩子，這件事讓我承受很大壓力
I tell you, son, this thing really came along and knocked my wind out.
讓我半夜驚醒，真的
It's got me up nights. That's the truth.
應該怎麼做
The right thing to do...
有時很難讓人明白
...sometimes it's hard to know what that is.
你明白了嗎？
Do you understand?
我需要你的幫助，孩子
I need your help, son.
如果我要繼續追查下去
If I'm going to move on this...
就不能有絲毫的疑點
...there can't be the least little shred of doubt.
我必須知道
I have to know...
你跟德弗瑞恩說的是事實嗎？
...if what you told Dufresne was the truth.
千真萬確
Yes, sir.
那麼你能在法官和陪審團面前……
Absolutely.
Would you be willing to swear before a judge and jury...
手放在聖經上……
...with your hand on the Good Book...
向上帝發誓嗎？
...and take an oath before Almighty God himself?
只要你給我這個機會
Just give me that chance.
那也正是我認為的
That's what I thought.
我想你已經聽說……
I'm sure by now you've heard.
那個壞消息了
Terrible thing.
一個這麼年青的人
A man that young...
還有一年就要出獄了，還想逃獄
...less than a year to go, trying to escape.
哈德利隊長被迫開槍
Broke Captain Hadley's heart to shoot him.
那是事實
Truly, it did.
我們不要再去提那件事了
We just have to put it behind us.
繼續生活
Move on.
我已經完了
I'm done.
一切己結束了
Everything stops.
找其他人幫你做吧
Get someone else to run your scams.
任何事都沒停下來
Nothing stops.
任何事
Nothing.
否則你在此繼續熬下去
Or you will do the hardest time there is.
再也沒有警衛保護你
No more protection from the guards.
我會把你從單人牢房轉到同性戀者那
I'll pull you out of that 1 -bunk Hilton and cast you down with the sodomites.
你會覺得你被火車操了
You'll think you've been fucked by a train.
至於圖書館？
And the library?
不存在了
Gone.
我們用書在院子堹N肉
Sealed off, brick by brick.
會被一塊塊的磚頭封閉起來
We'll have us a little book barbecue in the yard.
幾英里以外都能看見火焰
They'll see the flames for miles.
我們像土著人那樣圍著書跳舞
We'll dance around it like wild Injuns.
你明白我的意思了嗎？聽懂了嗎？
You understand me? Catching my drift?
或許我很愚蠢？
Or am I being obtuse?
再給他一個月時間考慮清楚
Give him another month to think about it.
我妻子曾說過我是個很難理解的人
My wife used to say I'm a hard man to know.
像本合著的書
Like a closed book.
她經常這樣抱怨
Complained about it all the time.
她很漂亮
She was beautiful.
上帝，我愛她
God, I loved her.
只是我不知道如何表達我的感情
I didn't know how to show it, that's all.
我殺了她，瑞德
I killed her, Red.
雖然不是我開的槍
I didn't pull the trigger...
但是我把她趕走的
...but I drove her away.
她是因我而死的
That's why she died, because of me...
因為我對她的態度
...the way I am.
那不能判你謀殺的
That don't make you a murderer.
只能說是壞丈夫
Bad husband, maybe.
你可以為此難過，但槍不是你開的
Feel bad about it if you want, but you didn't pull the trigger.
不是我殺的
No, I didn't.
是別人幹的
Somebody else did.
我在這堸竣F替死鬼
And I wound up in here.
運氣不好，我想
Bad luck, I guess.
霉運到處漂浮
It floats around.
總要有人承受的
It's got to land on somebody.
剛巧輪到我罷了
It was my turn, that's all.
我剛好碰上了它
I was in the path of the tornado.
我只是沒有想到會這麼久
I just didn't expect the storm would last as long as it has.
想過你有一天能出去嗎？
Think you'll ever get out of here?
我？
Me?
有
Yeah.
有一天，到我頭髮花白……
One day, when I got a long, white beard...
頭昏眼花的時候
...and two or three marbles rolling around upstairs.
我告訴你，我會到哪堨h
I tell you where I'd go.
聖哈塔尼奧
Zihuatanejo.
什麼？
Say what?
聖哈塔尼奧
Zihuatanejo.
在墨西哥
It's in Mexico.
太平洋中的一個小地方
A little place on the Pacific Ocean.
你知道墨西哥人怎麼形容太平洋的
You know what the Mexicans say about the Pacific?
他們說那堿O沒有記憶的地方
They say it has no memory.
那就是我想渡過餘生的地方
That's where I want to live the rest of my life.
一個沒有記憶的溫暖地方
A warm place with no memory.
開間小旅館
Open up a little hotel...
就在沙灘邊上
...right on the beach.
買艘不值錢的舊船回來
Buy some worthless old boat...
把它翻新
...and fix it up new.
載著我的客人
Take my guests out...
出海釣魚
...charter fishing.
聖哈塔尼奧
Zihuatanejo.
在那種地方，我需要個能找到東西的人
In a place like that, I could use a man that knows how to get things.
我覺得外面的社會可能不適合我
I don't think I could make it on the outside.
我的大半生都在這奡蝜L
I been in here most of my life.
我已經是這堛漱@部分了
I'm an institutional man now.
就像布魯克那樣
Just like Brooks was.
你看輕了你自己
You underestimate yourself.
我不這樣看
I don't think so.
在此我能供應物品給你，但是……
In here I'm the guy who can get things for you, sure, but...
在外面你只需要電話簿黃頁分類
...outside all you need is the Yellow Pages.
我不知道如何開始
Hell, I wouldn't know where to begin.
太平洋？
Pacific Ocean?
Shit.
那麼大的地方會嚇死我的
Scare me to death, something that big.
我不怕
Not me.
我沒開槍殺我妻子，我也沒開槍殺她的情人
I didn't shoot my wife, and I didn't shoot her lover.
不論我犯了什麼錯，我都已補償了
Whatever mistakes I made, I've paid for them and then some.
一間旅館和一條船
That hotel, that boat...
我要的並不太多
I don't think that's too much to ask.
我勸你不要再想了
You shouldn't be doing this to yourself.
那只是你的夢想罷了
This is just shitty pipe dreams.
墨西哥在遙遠的天邊，而你在這
Mexico is way down there and you're in here...
這才是現實
...and that's the way it is.
是的，是這樣
Yeah, right. That's the way it is.
它在遠方，而我在這
It's down there and I'm in here.
我想只有一個簡單的選擇
I guess it comes down to a simple choice.
要麼忙著活……
Get busy living...
要麼忙著死
...or get busy dying.
安迪
瑞德
如果你能出去的話，幫我做件事
If you ever get out of here, do me a favor.
當然可以，安迪，什麼事都行
Sure, Andy. Anything.
布克斯頓附近有個草場，你知道在哪媔隉H
There's a big hayfield up near Buxton. You know where Buxton is?
-那埵陶\多牧場 -有一個很特別……
- A lot of hayfields up there. - One in particular.
它有很長的石牆，北邊的盡頭有棵橡樹
It's got a long rock wall with a big oak tree at the north end.
像佛洛斯特的詩描繪的那樣 「佛洛斯特（Robert Frost）：美國著名詩人」
It's like something out of a Robert Frost poem.
那是我向我太太求婚的地方
It's where I asked my wife to marry me.
我們到那堨h野餐
We went there for a picnic...
還在橡樹下做愛
...and made love under that oak...
我向她求婚，她答應了
...and I asked and she said yes.
答應我，瑞德
Promise me, Red.
如果你出去的話
If you ever get out...
找到那
...find that spot.
在牆角下，有塊與眾不同的石頭……
At the base of that wall, there's a rock that has no earthly business in Maine.
一塊黑色的火山玻璃石
Piece of black, volcanic glass.
下面埋著我想給你的東西
Something's buried under it I want you to have.
是什麼，安迪？
What, Andy?
埋在那堛漪O什麼？
What's buried under there?
你自己挖出來……
You'll have to pry it up...
……就知道了
...to see.
不，我告訴你，他……
No, I'm telling you. The guy is...
他只是在開玩笑
He's talking funny.
我真的很擔心他
I'm really worried about him.
那就好好看著他吧
Let's keep an eye on him.
白天還可以，但晚上怎麼辦？
That's fine during the day, but at night he's all alone.
上帝
Oh, Lord.
什麼事？
What?
安迪今天到我這堥蚢L
Andy come down to the loading dock today.
他問我要了捆繩索
He asked me for a length of rope.
繩索？
Rope?
六英尺長
Six feet long.
那你給他了？
And you gave it to him.
當然為什麼不呢？
Sure. Why wouldn't I?
上帝！海伍德
Jesus! Heywood.
我怎麼知道？
How was I supposed to know?
還記得布魯克斯嗎？
Remember Brooks Hatlen?
不，安迪不會那樣做的
Andy would never do that.
永遠不會
Never.
我不敢肯定
I don't know.
人總有脆弱的一刻
Every man has his breaking point.
快點要收工了
Lickety-split. Want to get home.
還差一點點了
Just about finished, sir.
今晚有三筆存款
Three deposits tonight.
把我的衣服拿到洗衣處去
Get my stuff down to the laundry.
還要擦一下我的鞋子
And shine my shoes.
我要它們看起來像鏡子一樣亮，好的，先生
- I want them looking like mirrors. - Yes, sir.
你能回來真好，安迪
It's good having you back.
你不在的話，一切都不一樣了
Place wasn't the same without you.
熄燈
Lights out!
那是個輾轉難眠的長夜
I've had some long nights in stir.
孤獨的黑暗中只有思想
Alone in the dark with nothing but your thoughts...
時間像把快刀
... time can draw out like a blade.
那是我一生中最漫長的夜晚
That was the longest night of my life.
清點人數
Give me a count!
南邊三樓，人齊了
Tier 3 south, clear!
二樓245囚室的人不見了
Man missing on tier 2, cell 245!
德弗瑞恩！
Dufresne!
快出來！不要耍花樣
Come out. You're holding up the show!
別要我下來打爆你的頭
Don't make me come down or I'll thump your skull for you!
他媽的，你不要耽誤我，我還有很多事要做
Damn it, you're putting me behind! I got a schedule to keep.
你最好是病了或者死了
You'd better be sick or dead in there. I shit you not!
你聽到了嗎？
You hear me?
啊，我的上帝！
Oh, my Holy God.
查問這堛漕C一個犯人
I want every man on this cellblock questioned.
-從他的好朋友開始 -誰？
- Start with that friend of his. - Who?
他！
打開237號的門
Open 237.
你什麼意思，「他不在這了」？別跟我說這種話
What do you mean, "He just wasn't here"? Don't say that to me.
別再這樣說
Don't tell me that again.
但是長官，他真的不在那
But sir, he wasn't.
我看得見！你認為我瞎了嗎？
I can see that, Haig! Think I'm blind?
這就是你想說的嗎？
Is that what you're saying?
-我瞎了嗎？ -沒有！長官
- Am I blind, Haig? - No, sir!
那你呢？你瞎了嗎？
What about you. You blind?
-告訴我這是什麼？ -昨晚的查房記錄
- Tell me what this is. - Last night's count.
你看到德弗瑞恩的名字嗎？我確定，就在那
You see Dufresne's name there? I sure do. Right there.
「德弗瑞恩」
"Dufresne."
他熄燈的時候
He was in his cell...
還在囚室堛
...at lights out.
因此今早他也應該在
Reasonable he'd be here in the morning.
我要找到他
I want him found.
不是明天，不是早飯後，是現在
Not tomorrow, not after breakfast. Now!
是的，長官
Yes, sir.
快走
Let's go. Move your butts.
站好
Stand.
那麼？
Well?
那麼，什麼？
Well, what?
你們常在一起，親密得像做賊一樣
I see you two all the time. You're thick as thieves, you are.
他肯定對你說過些什麼
He must have said something.
沒有，先生，獄長
No, sir, Warden.
什麼都沒說
Not a word.
主啊，這是個奇跡
Lord, it's a miracle!
人就像屁一樣在風中消失了
Man vanished like a fart in the wind.
什麼都沒留下
Nothing left...
只剩下窗台上的石頭
...but some damn rocks on a windowsill.
和那牆上的小妞，問問她吧
And that cupcake on the wall. Let's ask her.
也許她知道些什麼
Maybe she knows.
你想說什麼？
What say there, fuzzy-britches? Feel like talking?
我想沒有
Guess not.
為什麼她有點特別？
Why should she be any different?
這是一個陰謀
This is a conspiracy.
肯定是的
That's what this is.
一個該死的大陰謀
One big, damn conspiracy!
所有人都有參與
And everyone's in on it!
包括她
Including her!
在1966年
In 1966...
安迪·德弗瑞恩從肖申克監獄……
... Andy Dufresne escaped...
逃了出去
... from Shawshank Prison.
他們只能找到泥塘中的囚衣……
All they found was a muddy set of prison clothes...
一塊肥皂……
... a bar of soap...
和一個很舊的手槌
... and an old rock hammer...
幾乎快被削成一小塊
... damn near worn down to the nub.
我曾認為用手槌要六百年才能掘通的隧道
I had thought it'd take a man 600 years to tunnel through the wall with it.
安迪用不到二十年就辦到了
Old Andy did it in less than 20.
安迪很喜歡地質學
Oh, Andy loved geology.
我能想像這歸功於他一絲不茍的本性
I imagine it appealed to his meticulous nature.
如果這埵酗@段冰河時期
An ice age here...
百萬年後，山脈就會在那塈峖
... million years of mountain building there.
地質學是關於壓力和時間的研究
Geology is the study of pressure and time.
需要的僅僅就是這些
That's all it takes, really.
壓力……
Pressure...
……和時間
... and time.
還有一張大海報
That and a big goddamn poster.
就像我說的那樣
Like I said...
監獄堛漱H都會找事情來消磨時間
... in prison, a man will do anything to keep his mind occupied.
看起來安迪的愛好是把他的牆搬運到廣場上
Seems Andy's favorite hobby was toting his wall out into the exercise yard...
每次一把
... a handful at a time.
我猜在湯姆被殺後
I guess after Tommy was killed...
安迪覺得他在此呆得已夠久了
... Andy decided he'd been here long enough.
盡快，我要回家了
Lickety-split. I want to get home.
我馬上就好了
I'm just about finished, sir.
今晚有三筆存款
Three deposits tonight.
安迪照他的吩咐
Andy did like he was told.
把鞋擦得閃閃發亮
Buffed those shoes to a high mirror-shine.
警衛完全沒有注意到
The guards simply didn't notice.
我也沒有
Neither did I.
說真的
I mean, seriously...
誰會留意別人穿的鞋子呢？
... how often do you really look at a man's shoes?
安迪朝向自由爬了五百碼
Andy crawled to freedom through 500 yards...
我難以想像有多臭的下水道
... of shit-smelling foulness I can't even imagine.
或許我只是不想去爬
Or maybe I just don't want to.
五百碼
Five hundred yards.
有五個足球場那麼長
That's the length of five football fields.
有半英里左右
Just shy of half a mile.
第二天早上，就在那海報被撕下來的時候
The next morning, right about the time Raquel was spilling her secret...
一個從未出現過的人
... a man nobody ever laid eyes on before...
走進了緬因州國家銀行
... strolled into the Maine National Bank.
在那一刻前，他從來是不存在的
Until that moment, he didn't exist.
-除了在紙上 -我可以幫忙嗎？
- Except on paper. - May I help you?
他有所有正確的身份證明文件……
He had all the proper ID...
駕駛執照、出生證明、社會安全證……
... driver's license, birth certificate, Social Security card...
簽名也是正確的
And the signature was a spot-on match.
不能再為你服務真的很遺憾
I must say I'm sorry to be losing your business.
希望你在國外生活愉快
I hope you'll enjoy living abroad.
謝謝
Thank you.
我想我會的
I'm sure I will.
先生，這是你的本票，還有別的嗎？
Here's your cashier's check, sir. Will there be anything else?
請問
Please.
你能幫我把它寄出嗎？
Would you add this to your outgoing mail?
我很樂意
I'd be happy to.
-再見 -走好，先生
Good day, sir.
史蒂文先生那天早上去了將近十二家銀行
Mr. Stevens visited nearly a dozen banks in the Portland area that morning.
加起來
All told, he blew town...
他總共提取了三十七萬諾頓獄長的錢
... with better than $370,000 of Warden Norton's money.
作為十九年的賠償
Severance pay for 19 years.
早上好，波特蘭時報
Good morning, Portland Daily Bugle.
「肖申克監獄,貪污謀殺」
「主的審判迅速降臨」
「親愛的典獄長,你說的對」
「得救之道,就在其中」
拜倫·哈德利？你有權保持沉默
Byron Hadley? You have the right to remain silent.
否則你所說的一切都將對你不利
If you give up this right, anything you say can be held against you in court.
我雖沒有親眼看到，但我聽說他被帶走時
I wasn't there to see, but I hear Byron Hadley sobbed like a girl...
哭得像個娘們
... when they took him away.
諾頓沒有靜靜離開的意思
Norton had no intention of going that quietly.
森姆·諾頓？
Samuel Norton.
我們有拘捕令，開門！
We have a warrant for your arrest. Open up.
開門吧
Open the door.
我不知是哪把鑰匙
I'm not sure which key.
別緊張，諾頓
Make it easy on yourself, Norton!
我想知道當子彈穿過他的頭的時候
I like to think the last thing that went through his head...
他在想些什麼
... other than that bullet...
是在想該死的安迪.德弗瑞恩到底是如何擊敗他？
... was to wonder how the hell Andy Dufresne ever got the best of him.
諾頓獄長一夥倒台之後
Not long after the warden deprived us of his company...
我收到了張明信片
... I got a postcard in the mail.
它是空白的，但是郵戳是……
It was blank, but the postmark said...
漢格堡，德薩斯州的
... Fort Hancock, Texas.
漢格堡
Fort Hancock...
就在邊境那
... right on the border.
安迪就是從那堨X國的
That's where Andy crossed.
當我想到他開車向南走的時候
When I picture him heading south in his own car with the top down...
我總會笑起來
... it always makes me laugh.
安迪·德弗瑞恩
Andy Dufresne...
爬過了那臭屎溝
... who crawled through a river of shit...
然後乾乾淨淨的到另一邊去了
... and came out clean on the other side.
安迪·德弗瑞恩
Andy Dufresne...
向太平洋進發
... headed for the Pacific.
哈德利抓住他的頭，對嗎？
Hadley's got him by the throat, right?
他說，「我相信他將會發生意外」
He says, " I believe this boy's about to have himself an accident."
我們跟他熟的老是談起安迪
Those of us who knew him best talk about him often.
我發誓，他總是帶來話題
I swear, the stuff he pulled...
「我的朋友可以要兩瓶啤酒」
"My friends could use a couple of beers."
他成功了
And he got it!
有時那令我傷心，雖然……
Sometimes it makes me sad, though...
安迪已經離開了
... Andy being gone.
我不得不提醒自己有些鳥是不能關在籠子堛
I have to remind myself that some birds aren't meant to be caged.
它們的羽毛太光亮
Their feathers are just too bright.
當它們飛走的時候
And when they fly away...
你會覺得把它們關起來是種罪惡
... the part of you that knows it was a sin to lock them up does rejoice.
但是
But still...
它們的離開讓你生活的地方空蕩蕩的
... the place you live in is that much more drab and empty that they're gone.
可能我只是想念我的朋友了
I guess I just miss my friend.
請坐
Please sit down.
瑞德
Ellis Boyd Redding...
你因終身監禁已被關了40年了
...your files say you've served 40 years of a life sentence.
你覺得你已改過了嗎？
You feel you've been rehabilitated?
改過？
Rehabilitated?
讓我想想
Well, now, let me see.
我不明白那是什麼意思
I don't have any idea what that means.
你有心理準備重新投入社會嗎？
It means you're ready to rejoin society...
我知道你們是怎麼想的，老弟
I know what you think it means, sonny.
對我來說那只是個用來掩飾的詞
To me it's just a made-up word.
政客用的詞語
A politician's word so that...
讓你們年青人能穿西裝打領帶
...young fellas like yourself can wear a suit and a tie...
有一份好工作
...and have a job.
你倒底想知道些什麼？
What do you really want to know?
我對自己所犯的罪感到後悔嗎？
Am I sorry for what I did?
你有後悔嗎？
Well, are you?
沒有一天我不感到後悔的
There's not a day goes by I don't feel regret.
不是因為我在監獄堙A或者你認為我該這樣
Not because I'm in here or because you think I should.
我回首過往
I look back on the way I was then...
一個年青的……
...a young...
愚蠢的孩子犯了大罪
...stupid kid who committed that terrible crime.
我想和他談談
I want to talk to him.
我想和他講講道理
I want to try and talk some sense to him.
告訴他做人道理
Tell him the way things are.
但已經不能了
But I can't.
那孩子已無影無蹤
That kid's long gone...
只剩下這個老人
...and this old man is all that's left.
我得這樣生活下去
I got to live with that.
改過？
Rehabilitated?
只是個狗屁的字眼
It's just a bullshit word.
你繼續蓋上你的印章吧，老弟，別再浪費我的時間了
So you go on and stamp your forms, sonny, and stop wasting my time.
說句實話
Because to tell you the truth...
我根本不在乎
...I don't give a shit.
「通過」
「布魯斯到此」
你的，小姐
Here you go, miss.
我可以去洗手間嗎？
Restroom break?
你不用每次都問我，去吧
You don't need to ask me every time you need to go take a piss. Just go.
四十年來我小便都要經過批准
Forty years I've been asking permission to piss.
不批准的話一滴都尿不出來
I can't squeeze a drop without say-so.
現實是很難面對的
There's a harsh truth to face.
我不習慣外面的生活
No way I'm going to make it on the outside.
我總在想怎樣才能違反假釋條例
All I do anymore is think of ways to break my parole...
那樣他們會把我再送進去
... so maybe they'd send me back.
生活在恐懼中是很可怕的
Terrible thing, to live in fear.
布魯克是知道的
Brooks Hatlen knew it.
他知道得太清楚了
Knew it all too well.
我只想回到能適合我的地方
All I want is to be back where things make sense.
令我不用再擔心受怕的地方
Where I won't have to be afraid all the time.
只有一件事阻止了我這麼做
Only one thing stops me.
我對安迪作出的承諾
A promise I made to Andy.
就在那
There it is.
非常感謝，先生
Much obliged, sir.
「布克斯頓」
親愛的瑞德
Dear Red:
若你能看到這封信，那你已經出來了
If you're reading this, you've gotten out...
……如果你已來了這麼遠，也許可以再前進一點
... and if you've come this far, maybe you'd come a bit further.
你還記得那個地方的名字，是嗎？
You remember the name of the town, don't you?
聖哈塔尼奧
Zihuatanejo.
我需要一個人和我一起工作
I could use a good man to help me get my project on wheels.
我期待你的到來，計劃已經擺好了
I'll keep an eye out for you, and the chessboard ready.
記住，瑞德
Remember, Red...
有希望是件好事情
... hope is a good thing...
也許是世間最好的事情
... maybe the best of things.
好的事情從不會逝去
And no good thing ever dies.
我希望這封信能見到你
I will be hoping that this letter finds you...
見到你很好
... and finds you well.
你的朋友
Your friend...
安迪
... Andy.
「要麼忙著活」
"Get busy living...
「要麼忙著死」
... or get busy dying. "
這話一點都沒錯
That's goddamn right.
「瑞德也來過」
我一生中第二次……
For the second time in my life...
犯了罪
... I'm guilty of committing a crime.
違反了假釋條例
Parole violation.
當然，我懷疑他們會因此設下路障
Of course I doubt they'll toss up any roadblocks for that.
尤其是像我這樣的老人家
Not for an old crook like me.
德薩斯州，漢格堡
Fort Hancock, Texas, please.
我發現我很激動，幾乎坐不住，思緒紛亂
I find I'm so excited I can barely sit still or hold a thought in my head.
這是一個自由人才能感受到的
I think it's the excitement only a free man can feel.
一個自由人開始了漫長的旅程
A free man at the start of a long journey...
伴隨著未知的結局
... whose conclusion is uncertain.
我希望我能成功越過邊界
I hope I can make it across the border.
我希望看見我的朋友，和他握手
I hope to see my friend and shake his hand.
我希望太平洋的海水如我夢中那樣的藍
I hope the Pacific is as blue as it has been in my dreams.
我希望……
I hope.
「謹此紀念亞倫格林」
劇終 謝謝收看
TLF中文字幕站 http://tlfsubs.eastgame.net